<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>The Rings of Saturn</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heart_of_Darkness#Historical_context"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/d/d1/Roi_des_belges.jpg" alt="Roi des Belges, the ship Conrad used to travel up the Congo" style="float:right"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On board The Nellie waiting for the turn of the tide, Marlow entertains his companions with the tale of a mission he undertook as an employee of a Belgian trading company, traveling up the Congo river. This entertainment, the framed story in Joseph Conrad&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heart_of_Darkness" title="Heart of Darkness, Wikipedia"&gt;Heart of Darkness&lt;/a&gt;, quickly becomes very dark indeed, as Marlow presses on through disease, destruction and death, increasingly preoccupied with tracing the elusive Mr Kurtz, until eventually, when it seems he can go no further, he comes to a clearing. Looking through his glasses he sees the slope of a hill on which stands a house. There was no enclosure or fence of any kind, says Marlow, but there had been one apparently, for near the house half-a-dozen slim posts remained in a row, roughly trimmed, and with their upper ends ornamented with round carved balls. The occupant of this house, a harlequin figure, a jester at the court of King Kurtz if you like, also appears in Terry Jones&amp;#8217; &lt;a href="http://www.fluidinfo.com/terry/2009/03/02/the-entrepreneurial-spirit-in-literature/"&gt;fluidinfo blog&lt;/a&gt;, and it was this blog article which sent me back to Conrad, his character Marlow, and his terrible journey.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unnamed harlequin figure Marlow encounters seems unaffected by the madness around him and &lt;a href="http://jon.es/terry.html"&gt;Terry Jones&lt;/a&gt; finds similarities between his attitude and that of an entrepreneur, quoting Marlow &amp;#8230; The glamour of youth enveloped his parti-coloured rags, his destitution, his loneliness, the essential desolation of his futile wanderings. For months &amp;#8212; for years &amp;#8212; his life hadn&amp;#8217;t been worth a day&amp;#8217;s purchase; and there he was gallantly, thoughtlessly alive, to all appearances indestructible solely by the virtue of his few years and of his unreflecting audacity &amp;#8230; words I found interesting in the context of the &lt;a href="http://www.fluidinfo.com/terry/" title="Terry Jones's fluidinfo blog"&gt;fluidinfo blog&lt;/a&gt;, which I have followed since hearing Terry Jones &lt;a href="http://www.pyconuk.org/talks_2007.html#36"&gt;speak at PyCon UK&lt;/a&gt; a couple of years ago.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fluidinfo.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.fluidinfo.com/images/fi-logo-cropped.png" alt="fluidinfo logo" style="float:right;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terry Jones is &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/terrycojones/status/1581462570"&gt;obsessed&lt;/a&gt; with connections and with organising the internet &amp;#8212; an investigation which begins with the realisation that organising is the wrong word. Library style portals pioneered in the early days of the web by the likes of alta vista and yahoo! &amp;#8212; these facades have crumbled, broken up by their brittle hierarchies and the inefficiency of dictionary search. In their place an army of robots follows links and crunches data, maintaining google&amp;#8217;s ever growing index. Yet even this empire will fall. Already the cracks begin to show: google urges us to organise, to use canonical resource locators, &lt;a href="http://is.gd/jlio"&gt;http://is.gd/jlio&lt;/a&gt;; instead, we reduce and redirect. Quotation and association lie at the heart of the web and better tools are being invented for labelling, sharing and shaping the flow of information. At the conference these were the ideas which Terry Jones conveyed to me and others in that enclosed room in the basement of the Birmingham Conservatoire, ideas which seemed novel at the time, yet which now seem to have gathered momentum. I hope his company, &lt;a href="http://www.fluidinfo.com" title="Fluidinfo, the next everything"&gt;Fluidinfo&lt;/a&gt; can exploit his vision.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="amazon"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0811214133?tag=wordalig-20"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/books/rings-of-saturn-cover.jpg" alt="Rings of Saturn cover"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It came as something of a shock, though, to see the connection between Terry Jones and Joseph Conrad. How can Marlow&amp;#8217;s harlequin remain unscathed by his circumstances? Because he is young and a fool. J&amp;oacute;sef Teodor Konrad Korzeniowksi, the Polish-born seaman, who would later become Joseph Conrad the great English writer &amp;#8212; Korzeniowksi experienced first hand the full horror of the entrepreneurialism which led to gross exploitation of the Congo; and by coincidence, when I read Terry Jones&amp;#8217; blog post, I had just finished re-reading WG Sebald&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0811214133?tag=wordalig-20" title="The Rings of Saturn, on Amazon, another great river"&gt;The Rings of Saturn&lt;/a&gt;, a book which touches on the life of Korzeniowksi amongst many other things. Like Marlow&amp;#8217;s story, WG Sebald&amp;#8217;s book centres on a voyage, in this case one undertaken by the author on foot through Suffolk in 1992, a date close to the birth of the web. Like the modern day blogger, Sebald quotes, pastes in images, connects. Unlike most bloggers, Sebald has the genius to assemble these parts into something beautiful and profound. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sebald had hoped his walk would dispel the emptiness which takes hold of him whenever he has completed a long stint of work, but, walking for hours on end through the countryside, he finds himself preoccupied  with the traces of destruction, reaching far into the past, that were evident even in that remote place. He finds Suffolk to be thinly-populated and declining fast. The North Sea has been over-fished and eats into the coastline. Blighted towns suffer from poverty, unemployment and neglect, while once great houses decay, their gardens becoming &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/sets/72157617288800804/"&gt;overgrown&lt;/a&gt;, their owners becoming eccentric, then mad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/3455678986/" title="Today there is no trace of it by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3543/3455678986_823c0b3abf_m.jpg" width="223" height="240" alt="Today there is no trace of it" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J&amp;oacute;sef Teodor Konrad Korzeniowksi, Sebald writes, became an employee of the Soci&amp;eacute;t&amp;eacute; Anonyme Belge pour le Commerce du Haut-Congo, an organisation whose legendary profits were built on a system of slave labour which was sanctioned by the shareholders and all the Europeans contracted to work in the new colony. On reaching Matadi, a desolate settlement (as Marlow later describes in Heart of Darkness), Korzeniowksi comes on a place where those who were racked by illness, starvation and toil had withdrawn to die. I began to distinguish the gleam of the eyes under the trees, says Marlow. Then, glancing down, I saw a face near my hand. The black bones reclined at full length with one shoulder against the tree, and slowly the eyelids and the sunken eyes looked up at me, enormous and vacant, a kind of blind, white flicker in the depths of the orbs, which died out slowly. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Korzeniowksi fell ill and would continue no further, though it would be some months before his return to Europe, and from then on protracted bouts of despair would alternate with his writing; but Marlow continues up-river, finally arriving at the clearing described at the start of this article, where he meets the young man whose spirit, to Terry Jones, has so much in common with entrepreneurialism &amp;#8230; I saw my mistake, says Marlow. These round knobs were not ornamental but symbolic; they were expressive and puzzling, striking and disturbing &amp;#8212; food for thought and also for the vultures if there had been any looking down from the sky; but at all events for such ants as were industrious enough to ascend the pole. They would have been even more impressive, those heads on stakes, if their faces had not been turned to the house. Only one, the first I had made out, was facing my way. I was not so shocked as you may think. The start back I had given was really nothing but a movement of surprise. I had expected to see a knob of wood there, you know. I returned deliberately to the first I had seen &amp;#8212; and there it was, black, dried, sunken, with closed eyelids &amp;#8212; a head that seemed to sleep at the top of that pole, and, with the shrunken dry lips showing a narrow white line of the teeth, was smiling, too, smiling continuously at some endless and jocose dream of that eternal slumber.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://jon.es/terry.html"&gt;&lt;img src="http://jon.es/images/idiot-only.png" alt="When I grow up I'm going to be..."/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll find &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0811214133?tag=wordalig-20" title="The Rings of Saturn, on Amazon, another great river"&gt;The Rings of Saturn&lt;/a&gt; filed under fiction but in fact it&amp;#8217;s a circular journey which combines autobiography, biography, and history into a strange and moving whole. It is a book which defies categorisation but that won&amp;#8217;t stop me from tagging it: compelling, profound, recommended.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-04-28</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/the-rings-of-saturn</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/the-rings-of-saturn</link>
<category>Books</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Software development checklist += 3</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Various people better qualified than me have created &lt;a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000043.html" title="The Joel Test"&gt;checklists&lt;/a&gt; for healthy software development &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/an-ideal-working-environment.html" title="An ideal working environment"&gt;environments&lt;/a&gt;. I won&amp;#8217;t be offering my own such list, but I would like to mention a couple of items which deserve a place on it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     Does your company have a good library? Can anyone order a book for this library, easily?
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Do team members attend conferences? Do they give presentations at conferences?
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Libraries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cm.bell-labs.com/cm/cs/cbook/"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://cm.bell-labs.com/cm/cs/cbook/covers/main.gif" alt="K &amp;amp; R 2nd edition cover"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope no one disputes the first item. Sure, many software developers like buying their own books; but they deserve access to company copies of favourite references rather than having to bring personal copies into work. And yes, equally many software developers can find better things than books to spend their own money on, but give them access to a good library and they may well make good use of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please, minimise infrastructure. Don&amp;#8217;t track who has which book: just understand that when a book gets taken home it should be returned in a timely fashion. Current editions of books should be available, as should multiple copies of popular books: don&amp;#8217;t waste time waiting for the company copy of &lt;a href="http://cm.bell-labs.com/cm/cs/cbook/"&gt;K&amp;amp;R&lt;/a&gt; to become available, get another. This simple infrastructure should extend to the maintenance of the library. A team knows which books it needs and which books it is interested in, and team members should be able to order these books without pre-approval.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conferences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2009"&gt;&lt;img src="http://accu.org/content/images/conferences/2009/accu2009web.png" alt="ACCU 2009 logo"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conferences aren&amp;#8217;t for everyone but events like the &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences"&gt;ACCU conference&lt;/a&gt; (being held in Oxford this week) provide an invaluable opportunity to step outside your own organisation and routine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re a C# programmer, say, attending ACCU won&amp;#8217;t be like going on a 5 day Microsoft certified .NET training course. For one thing, ACCU isn&amp;#8217;t trying to make a profit. More importantly, the ACCU &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2009/accu2009_schedule"&gt;schedule&lt;/a&gt; is varied and stimulating, with presentations from acknowledged world experts and &lt;a href="http://fellowhackers.com" title="Whois fellowhackers.com? Not stack overflow!"&gt;fellow hackers&lt;/a&gt;. Come with an open mind. Who knows what you&amp;#8217;ll learn?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.europython.eu"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.europython.eu/images/europython_logo.png" alt="Europython Logo"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I long ago decided that, for me, attending conferences was one of the most effective ways of continuing to develop as a programmer. I also quickly learned that a conference can be an intense experience, so I limit my exposure to them. This year, sadly, I&amp;#8217;m skipping ACCU. But I will be off to &lt;a href="http://www.europython.eu"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graeco-Latin_square" title="Graeco-Latin square, on Wikipedia. Order 10 would be better"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/88/GraecoLatinSquare-Order5.png" style="float:right;" alt="Graeco-Latin square, on Wikipedia"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll also be going to a &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/bshm/meetings/Fiction.html"&gt;Mathematics and Fiction&lt;/a&gt; workshop in Oxford. It&amp;#8217;s not aimed at software developers, but literate programmer Donald Knuth will be there, as will &lt;a href="http://web.princeton.edu/sites/fit/faculty/bellos.html"&gt;David Bellos&lt;/a&gt;, translator of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Vie_mode_d%27emploi#The_constraints" title="Life A User's Manual, Wikipedia"&gt;the ultimate algorithm-driven fiction&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Contributing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I suggest employers support developers who wish to attend conferences as part of their ongoing training. Should an employer allow staff to burn company time to develop presentations for these conferences?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without more specific detail, I really can&amp;#8217;t say. No two cases will be exactly alike. One thing I will say is that, increasingly, organisations realise the benefits of the kind of grass-roots advertising which can be had from sending people to conferences and letting them talk openly about the work they&amp;#8217;re doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;#8217;ve danced around that question, I&amp;#8217;ll end by asking another &amp;#8212; a third item for my incomplete checklist.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Does your company contribute towards the open source code which it uses?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-04-21</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/checklist-inc-3</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/checklist-inc-3</link>
<category>Books</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
