<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>ACCU 2013</title>
<description>&lt;img src="http://accu.org/content/images/conferences/2013/accu2013web.png" alt="ACCU 2013" /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Marick opened the second day of ACCU 2013 with a keynote presentation entitled: &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2013/accu2013_sessions#cheating_decline:acting_now_to_let_you_program_well_for_a_really_long_time"&gt;&amp;#8220;Cheating Decline: Acting now to let you program well for a really long time&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. He drew a distinction between effortful and automatic thinking. For example, we can drive a car along a clear road automatically but it requires considerable concentration to parallel park that same car. By tuning out unwanted signals crickets can locate their mates using minimal brainpower, and cricket players have no need of Newtonian dynamics to track the trajectory of a ball &amp;#8212; they apply a simple visual self-calibrating algorithm to catch out batsmen. Tango dancers disturb and re-establish invariants. A robot can walk for hours without thinking about what it&amp;#8217;s doing. Actually, if it&amp;#8217;s your job to park cars, you can probably do &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; without thinking; and this was Brian Marick&amp;#8217;s main cheat &amp;#8212; find the work practices which allow you to lean on your perceptions and so avoid effortful thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/rhu2xNIpgDE?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anthony Williams&amp;#8217; talk on &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2013/accu2013_sessions#c_11_features_and_real-world_code"&gt;C++11 Features and Real World code&lt;/a&gt; did require effortful thinking but that was what I&amp;#8217;d hoped for. He provided a concise and expert summary of the new language features in action, focusing on the biggest early winners. Leading with &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;range-for&lt;/code&gt;, he went on to talk about concurrency and move semantics. I learned that &lt;code&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt; functions can have a mutable qualifier. Ha!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;#8217;t resist &lt;a href="http://www.pvv.org/~oma/"&gt;Olve Maudal&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; C++11 pub quiz, appropriately held in the Marriot Hotel bar, for which we formed teams and mentally compiled and executed dodgy code, capturing standard output on an answer sheet. Some of the answers may well have have been implementation dependent but Olve specified an implementation: our answers should match &lt;strong&gt;this&lt;/strong&gt; laptop running &lt;strong&gt;this&lt;/strong&gt; software. I was simultaneously appalled by the limits of my knowledge on fundamental subjects such as integral promotion and initialisation order, and surprised by my ability to correctly predict the behaviour of some esoteric and perverse code. I&amp;#8217;m chastened and will be studying the answers in the cold light of day. Brian Marick may have advocated programming after a beer or two in his morning session, but the afternoon pub quiz proved that coffee works better for me!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A programmer&amp;#8217;s dozen (13, which is 12 counting from zero!) lightning talks kept the day crackling with energy. Ewan Milne chaired the session expertly, adeptly dispatching a birthday cake as proceedings commenced. I wish I could describe all the talks but you really had to be there. Phil Nash&amp;#8217;s use of the little known &lt;a href="http://ideone.com/jWHxu2"&gt;left arrow operator&lt;/a&gt; &amp;larr; got a well deserved response from the audience. Sander Hoogendoorn stuck the boot into &lt;a href="http://sanderhoogendoorn.com/blog/?p=1059"&gt;&amp;#8220;Agile Fluffiness&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://www.renaissancesoftware.net/blog/"&gt;James Grenning&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; talk on embedded development was a lightning keynote: hilarious, moving and, ultimately, tragic.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2013-04-11</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/accu-2013.html</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/accu-2013.html</link>
<category>Bristol</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>A race within a race</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In 2003 the route of the Bristol half marathon took runners out of the city, following the Portway along the base of the Avon Gorge before turning 180&amp;deg; and taking them straight back again. So runners heading out along one side of the road got to watch the faster runners in front of them, heading back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style="align:top;" href="http://www.runnerslife.co.uk/Guest-Runners/Nick-Rose"&gt;&lt;img width="150" height="200" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/nick-rose-then.jpg" alt="Nick Rose then"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;a style="align:top;" href="http://www.upandrunning.co.uk/shops/bristol.php"&gt;&lt;img width="150" height="200" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/nick-rose-now.jpg" alt="Nick Rose now"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of the Avon Gorge was probably lost on most competitors, myself included. What did impress me, though, was the sight of Nick Rose sprinting back along the Portway, his white hair swept back by his astonishing speed. Despite being 13 years older than me he completed the 13 mile race 13 minutes ahead of me. (I did beat &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Cram"&gt;Steve Cram&lt;/a&gt; though!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.bristolhalfmarathon.com/about/race-history/"&gt;2003 Bristol half marathon&lt;/a&gt; featured a &lt;strong&gt;race within a race&lt;/strong&gt;, the &amp;#8220;Legends Challenge&amp;#8221;, which reunited veteran British athletes Nick Rose, Steve Cram, Tim Hutchings, Hugh Jones, Steve Jones and Mike McLeod to compete against each other for the first time since the 1984 Los Angeles Olympics. Nick Rose won this race within a race, aged 52, in 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; place overall, with a time of just 1:11:08. This inspiring result set me wondering about another slice of the results: starting with a list of runners ordered by their finishing time in a race, select, in order, a sublist of runners who are getting younger. &lt;strong&gt;What is the longest such sublist?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I don&amp;#8217;t have access to the full results for the Bristol 2003 half marathon. Instead, here are the top 20 finishers in the 2008 &lt;a href="http://www.nycmarathon.org"&gt;New York marathon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/a-race-within-a-race.html#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     MARILSON GOMES DOS SANTOS, 31, M, 2:08:43
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     ABDERRAHIM GOUMRI, 32, M, 2:09:07
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     DANIEL RONO, 30, M, 2:11:22
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;PAUL TERGAT, 39&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:13:10
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     ABDERRAHIME BOURAMDANE, 30, M, 2:13:33
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;ABDI ABDIRAHMAN, 31&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:14:17
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     JOSH ROHATINSKY, 26, M, 2:14:23
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     JASON LEHMKUHLE, 31, M, 2:14:30
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     HOSEA ROTICH, 29, M, 2:15:25
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;BOLOTA ASMEROM, 30&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:16:37
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;LUKE HUMPHREY, 27&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:18:38
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     HENDRICK RAMAALA, 36, M, 2:19:11
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     MOHAMMED AWOL, 30, M, 2:19:13
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;KASSAHUN KABISO, 25&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:19:54
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     JACOB FREY, 27, M, 2:20:17
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;GENNA TUFA, 24&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:20:23
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;KYLE SHACKLETON, 22&lt;/strong&gt;, M, 2:20:38
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     TEKLU TEFERA DENEKE, 29, M, 2:20:47
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     BOAZ CHEBOIYWO, 30, M, 2:21:40
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     DERESSE DENIBOBA, 26, M, 2:21:54
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see Paul Tergat, 39, finished ahead of the younger runner Abdi Abdirahman, 31, who beat Bolota Asmerom, 30, etc., giving a sublist of 7 runners which fits our criteria. Certainly this isn&amp;#8217;t the only such sublist of this small sample, but is there a longer one?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few minutes we may convince ourselves we&amp;#8217;ve found an optimal solution. How would you approach this problem for the full results list, ending with YURIKO OKADA, 59, F, 9:59:58 in 38096&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; place?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nyc-architecture.com/BRI/BR-010.htm" title="How many runners?"&gt;&lt;img width="300" src="http://www.nyc-architecture.com/BRI/Verrazano-Narrows_Bridge_New_York_City_Marathon_2.jpg" alt="How many runners?"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be discussing this problem in the next few posts, so please make sure you&amp;#8217;re &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;subscribed&lt;/a&gt; to read on. In the meanwhile, here&amp;#8217;s a picture of the Avon Gorge taken from the western pier of the Clifton Suspension bridge. You can see the Portway down at the bottom. Nick Rose is a past winner of the Bristol Half Marathon. In 1979 &lt;a href="http://www.nationmaster.com/encyclopedia/Half-marathon#World_record_progression_-_Men"&gt;he set a world record time&lt;/a&gt; for the distance of 1:02:36, and his &lt;a href="http://hem.bredband.net/athletics/atb-m59.htm"&gt;personal best of 1:01:03&lt;/a&gt; still stands as a British record. He lives in Bristol, now working at &lt;a href="http://www.upandrunning.co.uk/shops/bristol.php"&gt;&amp;#8220;Up and Running&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; in Westbury Park, and he continues to participate in the sport.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/3163729064/" title="Avon Gorge and Clifton Suspension Bridge by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3120/3163729064_6f0feec1b8.jpg" width="500" height="154" alt="Avon Gorge and Clifton Suspension Bridge" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/a-race-within-a-race.html#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#8217;m using capital letters since these names are scraped directly from the &lt;a href="http://www.nycmarathon.org"&gt;New York Marathon website&lt;/a&gt;, which uses capital letters almost exclusively, except for non-ascii athletes such as CORN&amp;eacute; VAN OIRSCHOT.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-03-04</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/a-race-within-a-race.html</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/a-race-within-a-race.html</link>
<category>Bristol</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
