<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>comp.lang.name?</title>
<description>&lt;h3&gt;How the Python became&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guido van Rossum had a problem: &lt;a href="http://python-history.blogspot.com/2009/01/personal-history-part-1-cwi.html"&gt;what to call his new language&lt;/a&gt;? Computer language names often tip a hat to their predecessors, as &lt;strong&gt;Ruby&lt;/strong&gt; does to &lt;strong&gt;Perl&lt;/strong&gt;, for example. In this case the immediate predecessor, &lt;strong&gt;ABC&lt;/strong&gt;, had itself changed from &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; because it got mistaken for &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;, and the suggestion ABC &amp;#8220;made programming easy as ABC&amp;#8221; failed to convince Guido. So he dropped the alphabetic sequencing. Rather than tip a hat he picked a name from one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I picked the first thing that came to mind, which happened to be &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Python%27s_Flying_Circus"&gt;Monty Python&amp;#8217;s Flying Circus&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite comedy troupes. The reference felt suitably irreverent for what was essentially a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skunkworks_project"&gt;&amp;#8220;skunkworks project&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. The word &amp;#8220;Python&amp;#8221; was also catchy, a bit edgy, and at the same time, it fit in the tradition of naming languages after famous people, like Pascal, Ada, and Eiffel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Animals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/3215793436/" title="ya(k|cc) came?l a[uw]k "&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3431/3215793436_6840bb27b3_m.jpg" width="174" height="240" alt="yacc caml awk" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Guido van Rossum held out for some time against Python being associated with snakes, he eventually &lt;a href="http://personal.ee.surrey.ac.uk/Personal/L.Wood/softwear/" title="At last GvR embraces the snake"&gt;capitulated&lt;/a&gt;. Blame the animal cover lovers at O&amp;#8217;Reilly! As it happens, I rate the reptile as highly as the comedians. I also like languages with animal names. Perhaps &lt;strong&gt;Yacc&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Awk&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Caml&lt;/strong&gt; also started life as skunkworks?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Naming words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_(mythology)"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/20/Virgil_Solis_-_Apollo_Python.jpg/350px-Virgil_Solis_-_Apollo_Python.jpg" alt="Apollo slaying Python"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a noun &amp;#8212; what we called a &amp;#8220;naming word&amp;#8221; at junior school. Python is also a proper noun: in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_(mythology)" title="Python (mythology)"&gt;Greek Mythology&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;she&lt;/strong&gt; was the earth-dragon of Delphi. It&amp;#8217;s hardly surprising when language creators opt for nouns, often proper, frequently female: &lt;strong&gt;Ada&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Miranda&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Ruby&lt;/strong&gt;, for example. Also, &lt;strong&gt;Java&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Pascal&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Haskell&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8212; oh, yes, and &lt;strong&gt;Delphi&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Single characters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve already mentioned &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;, which I guess is a (homophone of a) girl&amp;#8217;s name. It&amp;#8217;s also a well rounded character found near the front of the alphabet. Alphabetically, B comes before C, and the language B features amongst &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#8217;s predecessors. When Bjarne Stroustrup built object-oriented features on top of C, his new language became known as &amp;#8220;new C&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;C with classes&amp;#8221;. The former was disrespectful to C, which risked becoming &amp;#8220;old C&amp;#8221;, and the latter failed to excite. The final name, &lt;strong&gt;C++&lt;/strong&gt;, was an inspired choice, even if some have pointed out &lt;strong&gt;++C&lt;/strong&gt; would be more correct.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C#&lt;/strong&gt; squeezes more juice from the pun. Pronounced &amp;#8220;See Sharp!&amp;#8221;, the name has a commanding ring to it, and if you look within the hash symbol, #, you can make out redoubled ++ signs. Shouldn&amp;#8217;t it &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_Sharp_(programming_language)#Language_name"&gt;be written C&amp;#x266f;&lt;/a&gt; though, or should we really pronounce it &amp;#8220;See Hash&amp;#8221;? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the + and the # characters have special semantics within URLs. How many C++ and C# blog posts end up being tagged &amp;#8220;C&amp;#8221;, I wonder? For similar reasons I guess it&amp;#8217;s still impractical to name a language &lt;b&gt;&amp;lambda;&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;&amp;mu;&lt;/b&gt;, unless you&amp;#8217;re prepared to accept that name being spelled &lt;strong&gt;lambda&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;mu&lt;/strong&gt;, that is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; really does look like a great language in the C and C++ tradition, but its name lacks imagination. Enough alphabet already!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Doing words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; are both strong, active verbs. Nothing beats being and seeing. Writers like verbs. Verbs make things happen, just like programming languages. Maybe &lt;strong&gt;Lisp&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Scheme&lt;/strong&gt; sound a bit geeky, sleazy even, but I like them. They&amp;#8217;re great names. Ever wonder how &lt;strong&gt;Bash&lt;/strong&gt; bludgeoned its way to shell domination? &lt;strong&gt;Squeak&lt;/strong&gt; is a great play on &lt;strong&gt;Smalltalk&lt;/strong&gt;. Knitters &lt;a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/purl"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;perl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Etc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.lancearmstrong.com/"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/lance-armstrong.jpg" alt="Lance Armstrong, champion cyclist"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjectives and adverbs are poorly represented. &lt;strong&gt;Groovy&lt;/strong&gt; comes to mind, but not a lot else. Plenty of language names are (or once were) acronyms and abbreviations: as names, I prefer the ones you can read over the mouthfuls of consonants. On this basis, &lt;strong&gt;Fortran&lt;/strong&gt; pips &lt;strong&gt;PL/I&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Sequel&lt;/strong&gt; beats &lt;strong&gt;Ess Queue El&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve listed some great computer languages with great names. Can a good name shape a language&amp;#8217;s success? Well, certainly it can&amp;#8217;t hurt. Names matter. Lance Armstrong is surely the name of a champion, the kind of guy who can beat testicular cancer and win the world&amp;#8217;s toughest endurance event 7 times in a row. Check out his &lt;a href="http://www.lancearmstrong.com/"&gt;flash heavy website&lt;/a&gt;. Whereas the more gently named Tim Henman never quite fulfilled his tennis potential, and I can&amp;#8217;t even connect to &lt;a href="http://www.timhenman.org"&gt;www.timhenman.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, can a poor name stand in the way of success? &lt;strong&gt;ABC&lt;/strong&gt; has become (part of Python&amp;#8217;s) history. I think it&amp;#8217;s fair to say that, at this point, the weakly-named &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; has gained respect rather than presence. On the other hand, &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt; is a poor name too, and &lt;strong&gt;ECMAScript&lt;/strong&gt; is worse, but it&amp;#8217;s a fine language which can claim to be more widely deployed than any other.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a name="feedback"&gt;Feedback&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;div id="feedback_div"&gt;&lt;ol id="feedback" class="feedback"&gt;&lt;li class="feedbackitem"&gt;&lt;div class="author"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Jez&lt;/cite&gt; 2009-01-23&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Names are important.  Choosing a good name for something is very difficult, and I know from past experience that you don&amp;#8217;t usually get a second go.  The humorous code name you chose almost certainly won&amp;#8217;t get changed later, and you&amp;#8217;ll be talking about &amp;#8220;using the Linguini server to add the zubins&amp;#8221; for ever.  Yes, that&amp;#8217;s a real example.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite cartoons, The Secret Show, is a comedy spy thriller.  The agency head takes security &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; seriously, and so his name is changed daily.  He&amp;#8217;s constantly undermined by being assigned ridiculous names - Mimzy Woowoo, Pimlico Buttonfluff, Princess Fairycakes, and so on.  In one episode his new name is Rock Justice, and his chest swells with pride.  Sadly though, it was just a dream.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class="feedbackitem" id="feedback-1000"&gt;&lt;div class="author"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;matt burns&lt;/cite&gt; 2009-01-28&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m sure I&amp;#8217;m not alone in pronouncing things incorrectly due to many of the things I learn being done so by reading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;C# was one example because for quite a while I pronounced it &amp;#8220;see hash&amp;#8221; in my head until I descovered it should be &amp;#8220;see sharp&amp;#8221;. I still occasionally slip out with kay-sh instead of cah-sh for cache.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#8217;t know that # and &amp;#x266f; were different symbols but now I do I feel less stupid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Wikipedia does mention that the language is actually C&amp;#x266f; but the # character is merely used to represent the &amp;#x266f; for simplicity.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class="feedbackitem"&gt; 
&lt;div class="author"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Thomas Guest&lt;/cite&gt; 2009-02-02&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="content"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;re definitely not alone, Matt. One thing which bugs me is when a name is spelled in a way which makes guessing its pronunciation hard.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cuil search engine, for example, which we&amp;#8217;re meant to pronounce &amp;#8220;cool&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Much as I like lighttpd, how are you supposed to say it? Lighty, apparently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Val-grinned&amp;#8221;, not &amp;#8220;Val-grind&amp;#8221;. Don&amp;#8217;t feed bad, &lt;a href="http://valgrind.org/docs/manual/faq.html#faq.pronounce"&gt;everyone gets it wrong at first&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-01-21</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/complangname</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/complangname</link>
<category>Etc</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
