<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Unit Tests Questioned: Reading List</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed &lt;a href="http://swanseasdc.co.uk/events/why-service-oriented-architecture/"&gt;talking about unit testing&lt;/a&gt; last night, and would like to thank &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SwanseaSDC"&gt;Swansea Software Development Community&lt;/a&gt; and especially Viv Richards for organising the event, &lt;a href="https://swansea.techhub.com/"&gt;TechHub&lt;/a&gt; for the venue, and everyone who turned up to listen, ask questions and offer feedback.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Up first &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thomasguest"&gt;@thomasguest&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ssdc?src=hash"&gt;#ssdc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/4nEqh0ErZr"&gt;pic.twitter.com/4nEqh0ErZr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; SSDC (@SwanseaSDC) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SwanseaSDC/status/826137883341885441"&gt;January 30, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slides are available &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You&amp;#8217;ll find links in the slide deck to the various papers and articles I referenced, but for convenience I&amp;#8217;m listing them here with some notes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gwern.net/docs/1996-hoare.pdf" title="Tony Hoare, How Did Software Get So Reliable Without Proof? (PDF)"&gt;How Did Software Get So Reliable Without Proof?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; by Sir Tony Hoare, published in 1996, is a considered and authoritative paper, in which the author calls into question much of his own research. It&amp;#8217;s not necessary to prove your programs correct, he writes, you can create systems which are both large and reliable using more pragmatic techniques. Since then, his conviction has strengthened. I had the privilege of attending his keynote at &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/europython-2009"&gt;Europython 2009&lt;/a&gt;, when he spoke about the science of computing and the engineering of software (this same talk is available on &lt;a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/tony-hoare-computing-engineering"&gt;InfoQ&lt;/a&gt;). His closing slide stated: One day, software will be the most reliable component of every product which contains it; and software engineering will be the most dependable of all engineering professions.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="http://rbcs-us.com/documents/Why-Most-Unit-Testing-is-Waste.pdf" title="Why Most Unit Testing is Waste (PDF)"&gt;Why Most Unit Testing is Waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; by James O Coplien calls out the unit testing zealots and makes the point that testers should be skeptical.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sqlite.org/testing.html" title="How SQLite Is Tested"&gt;How SQLite Is Tested&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; details what it takes to make bomb-proof software. Most of the tests described are system level tests. It&amp;#8217;s an impressive document which proves that writing tests requires creativity, determination and maybe even a sprinkling of malice.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="https://testing.googleblog.com/2016/05/flaky-tests-at-google-and-how-we.html" title="Flaky Tests at Google and How We Mitigate Them, John Micco"&gt;Flaky Tests at Google and How We Mitigate Them&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; is an honest and all too familiar tale of unreliable tests. However hard you try to eradicate test instabilities, it seems they creep back in at the same rate.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/testing-culture.html" title="Goto Fail, Heartbleed, and Unit Testing Culture"&gt;Goto Fail, Heartbleed, and Unit Testing Culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; argues unit tests would have trapped some notorious bugs in low level security software. It goes on to describe in detail the changing culture of the Google Web Server team, which successfully adopted a test-focused regime. There&amp;#8217;s some good advice on de-flaking, so I hope the author connected with his suffering colleagues.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="https://staff.fnwi.uva.nl/p.vanemdeboas/knuthnote.pdf" title="The correspondence between Donald E. Knuth and Peter van Emde Boas on priority deques during the spring of 1977"&gt;The correspondence between Donald E. Knuth and Peter van Emde Boas on priority deques during the spring of 1977&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; provides the background and context of Donald Knuth&amp;#8217;s famous quotation, &amp;#8220;Beware of bugs in the above code; I have only proved it correct, not tried it&amp;#8221;. It&amp;#8217;s a a witty admonition but Donald Knuth isn&amp;#8217;t joking. Don&amp;#8217;t trust code until you&amp;#8217;ve run it. Better, run it repeatedly through automated tests.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-02-01</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned-reading-list</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned-reading-list</link>
<category>Knuth</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Knuth visited, Brains Limited</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Lucky me, I &lt;strong&gt;did&lt;/strong&gt; get a ticket to see Professor Donald Knuth deliver the &lt;a href="http://www.bcs.org/content/ConWebDoc/38048"&gt;2011 Turing Lecture&lt;/a&gt; at Cardiff University. He started out by saying he&amp;#8217;d been wanting to come here ever since seeing Yellow Submarine in the 60s because of some &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0063823/quotes"&gt;dialogue&lt;/a&gt; which goes something like:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;What do you call a big school of whales?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;A University of Wales.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a fine country Wales is for a computer scientist, he continued, you have a place called &lt;a href="http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=login&amp;amp;aq=&amp;amp;sll=53.800651,-4.064941&amp;amp;sspn=17.130747,46.538086&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hq=&amp;amp;hnear=Login,+Whitland,+United+Kingdom&amp;amp;ll=51.837475,-4.745407&amp;amp;spn=0.279173,0.727158&amp;amp;z=11"&gt;Login&lt;/a&gt;. A village in Pembrokeshire, someone in the audience chipped in, it&amp;#8217;s very beautiful. Wonderful, all the more reason to visit!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Openings over, the lecture turned into a question and answer session. If I&amp;#8217;m honest, I&amp;#8217;d have preferred something more formal, but having just completed &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~uno/taocp.html"&gt;TAOCP4A&lt;/a&gt;, all 900 pages of it, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; Volume 8 of his collected papers, the &amp;#8220;dessert&amp;#8221; edition of the series on &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~uno/fg.html"&gt;fun and games&lt;/a&gt;, Professor Knuth was in a holiday mood, and it was a delight to hear him field questions on the future of computer science, P = NP, literate programming, analog computers, brute force vs. elegance, and whether the increase in computing power diminishes the art of programming.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, computers grow exponentially more powerful &amp;#8212; but human appetites grow yet more quickly. And even if you have all of that power, can you be sure the computers are getting the right answers? This afternoon, Professor Knuth said, while strolling through Cardiff, he&amp;#8217;d seen the famous brewery &lt;strong&gt;Brains &amp;amp; Co. Ltd.&lt;/strong&gt; and thought, yes, that&amp;#8217;s about right. Brains limited.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/arkadyevna/253441813/" title="BRAINS BRAINS BRAINS by Arkadyevna, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/106/253441813_b1673d90a8.jpg" width="500" height="334" alt="BRAINS BRAINS BRAINS" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thanks to Arkadyevna for permission to use her wonderful &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/arkadyevna/253441813/"&gt;photo.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2011-02-03</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/knuth-visited-brains-limited</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/knuth-visited-brains-limited</link>
<category>Knuth</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Undogfooding</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;David Jones perfectly &lt;a href="http://drj11.wordpress.com/2009/07/04/tony-hoare-man-of-science/"&gt;captures the look and feel&lt;/a&gt; of Sir Tony Hoare&amp;#8217;s presentation at &lt;a href="http://www.europython.eu"&gt;Europython 2009&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tony Hoare is clearly old skool. His slides had the calm and aged patina of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overhead_projector"&gt;OHP&lt;/a&gt; era, and I thought they were all the better for that. If you have a message, then that message can be conveyed without all the flash and shine that PowerPoint tempts you with (although, being a Microsoft man, of course his slides &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; in PowerPoint). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://docs.python.org/library/turtle.html#module-turtle"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/my-1st-turtle.png" alt="My first turtle sketch"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the parenthetical comment: Tony Hoare works for Microsoft and he uses Microsoft software, an activity developers refer to as &lt;a href="http://catb.org/jargon/html/D/dogfood.html"&gt;&amp;#8220;eating your own dogfood&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. Also eating dogfood at Europython, &lt;a href="http://www.europython.eu/talks/speakers/index.html#lingl_gregor"&gt;Gregor Lingl&lt;/a&gt; employed his very own &lt;a href="http://docs.python.org/library/turtle.html#module-turtle"&gt;turtle&lt;/a&gt; to guide the audience through a nifty presentation belying the reptile&amp;#8217;s slow-and-steady reputation. I&amp;#8217;ve always enjoyed sketching code using the Python interpreter, and sketching pictures with a turtle feels very pythonic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="typocode"&gt;&lt;div class="codetitle"&gt;My first turtle sketch&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;Python 3.1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from turtle import *
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; shape('turtle')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; circle(100)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; fillcolour('red')
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
NameError: name 'fillcolour' is not defined
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; fillcolor('red')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; begin_fill(); circle(100); end_fill()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def grey(pc): c = pc/100; fillcolor(c, c, c)
... 
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; clear()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def doit(r): begin_fill(); grey(r); circle(r); end_fill()
... 
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; for r in range(100): doit(r)
... 
^C^C
Traceback (most recent call last):
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; clear()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; for r in range(100, 0, -5): doit(r)
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; fillcolor('white')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; forward(150)

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregor Lingl&amp;#8217;s session at Europython wasn&amp;#8217;t the only one delivered using software developed by the presenter. What would be the opposite of eating your own dogfood, I wondered? Abusing someone else&amp;#8217;s software, perhaps.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;After one too many bad presentations at a meeting in January 2000, I decided to see if I could do something about it. &amp;#8212; &lt;a href="http://norvig.com/Gettysburg/making.html" title="The Making of the Gettysburg PowerPoint Presentation"&gt;Peter Norvig&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m fairly sure Peter Norvig had no part in PowerPoint&amp;#8217;s development. In a &lt;a href="http://norvig.com/Gettysburg"&gt;hilarious satire&lt;/a&gt; he skewers the popular presentation tool with its own Autocontent Wizard.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://norvig.com/Gettysburg/index.htm"&gt;&lt;img src="http://norvig.com/Gettysburg/img001.gif" width="500px" height="375px" alt="Gettysburg PPT, slide 1"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back on the subject of overhead projectors, I saw one put to good use by another eminent old-skooler, Donald Knuth, at the recent &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/bshm/meetings/Fiction.html"&gt;Mathematics and Fiction&lt;/a&gt; workshop in Oxford. Asked by passport control at London Heathrow if he&amp;#8217;d be visiting Oxford on a business trip or a pleasure trip, Knuth had answered: no, he&amp;#8217;d come on a ego trip.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knuth was in Oxford to talk to his fans about about &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/sn.html"&gt;Surreal Numbers&lt;/a&gt;, a       book he wrote in just a couple of weeks in 1973 while taking a break from working on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Art_of_Computer_Programming"&gt;The Art of Computer Programming&lt;/a&gt; in a hotel in Oslo, and which may well be the only example of a mathematical &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surreal_numbers"&gt;theory&lt;/a&gt; first published in fictional form.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/sn.html"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/books/surreal-numbers.jpg" width="240px" height="240px" alt="Surreal Numbers book cover" style="float:right;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the workshop Knuth had gone back to his files and found his working notes, the original hotel brochure, photos, hand-written reviews by P&amp;oacute;lya and others, though he couldn&amp;#8217;t locate the paper napkin on which &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Horton_Conway"&gt;John Horton Conway&lt;/a&gt; had sketched the axioms underpinning the number system a few months before&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/undogfooding#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; Knuth had copied this source material onto acetates which he then sorted and shuffled on the OHP according to the direction his reminiscences and questions from the audience took him.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Tony Hoare, Donald Knuth wasn&amp;#8217;t making a formal presentation, but I was struck by some advantages offered by the OHP. For one, the process of getting slides displayed seemed foolproof &amp;#8212; at Europython we had the usual catalogue of computer/screen interface glitches (unwanted dialog boxes popping up, batteries dying, screensavers kicking in, missing Mac display dongles, delays while rebooting Ubuntu, alignment issues). The OHP also facilitated a dynamic presentation style: Knuth accessed his slides at random, composing screens from more than one slide on the fly, and pointing to areas of interest directly using a finger. He didn&amp;#8217;t modify his slides during the session by writing on them, but that would also have been possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a supreme example of dogfood consumption, a couple of years after publishing Surreal Numbers Knuth took a rather longer break from TAOCP to work on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TeX"&gt;TeX&lt;/a&gt;, a typesetting system whose results match the beauty of his writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align:center"&gt;&amp;sect;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230; You get surreal numbers by playing games. I used to feel guilty in Cambridge that I spent all day playing games, while I was supposed to be doing mathematics. Then, when I discovered surreal numbers, I realized that playing games IS mathematics. &amp;#8212; &lt;a href="http://www.gap-system.org/~history/Quotations/Conway.html"&gt;John Horton Conway&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/undogfooding#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; In fact, he&amp;#8217;d lost the napkin before his stay in the hotel in Oslo, which explains the difference between the axioms used in Surreal Numbers and the ones originally suggested by John Horton Conway.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-07-08</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/undogfooding</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/undogfooding</link>
<category>Knuth</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Good maths, bad computers</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Do you like maths and computers? If so, I recommend Mark Chu-Carroll&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/goodmath"&gt;Good Math, Bad Math&lt;/a&gt; blog. Mathematicians strive for precision and clarity, which creates a natural tension with the more pragmatic world of computer programming. As Donald Knuth famously &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/faq.html"&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beware of bugs in the above code; I have only proved it correct, not tried it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Mark Chu-Carroll shared &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/goodmath/2009/03/the_blog_and_the_book.php"&gt;a precise formula&lt;/a&gt; for solving that most slippery computing problem of them all &amp;#8212; figuring out a project schedule.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[One of my favorite managers] said that when a programmer gives you an estimate of how long something should take, multiply it by two and increase the unit. So if they say it&amp;#8217;ll take a day, assume two weeks. If they say a week, assume two months. In my experience, it&amp;#8217;s actually a really good predictor.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And if they say it&amp;#8217;ll take 5 months to complete a novel &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TeX#History"&gt;digital typesetting program&lt;/a&gt;, expect delivery 10 years later&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly Mark Chu-Carroll&amp;#8217;s metric is of more practical use than &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofstadter%27s_law"&gt;Hofstadter&amp;#8217;s self-referential law&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#8217;d like to see it built into project planning tools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematicians are equally precise about random numbers, a notorious source of computing issues. I also recommend John D. Cook&amp;#8217;s blog, &lt;a href="http://www.johndcook.com/blog/"&gt;The Endeavour&lt;/a&gt;, which covers a broad range of mathematical and programming topics. In a &lt;a href="http://www.johndcook.com/blog/2009/03/16/quasi-random-sequences-in-art-and-integration/"&gt;recent article&lt;/a&gt; he points out why quasi-random numbers can sometimes be better than truly random numbers.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-03-17</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/good-maths-bad-computers</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/good-maths-bad-computers</link>
<category>Knuth</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Life, user manuals, recursive pictures</title>
<description>&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocreading-what-to-read" name="toc0" id="toc0"&gt;Reading what to read&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocrecursive-product-packaging" name="toc1" id="toc1"&gt;Recursive product packaging&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocfractals" name="toc2" id="toc2"&gt;Fractals&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocfractals-in-nature" name="toc3" id="toc3"&gt;Fractals in nature&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocwindows-in-windows" name="toc4" id="toc4"&gt;Windows in windows&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocrecursive-paintings-and-prints" name="toc5" id="toc5"&gt;Recursive paintings and prints&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocvalenes-masterpiece" name="toc6" id="toc6"&gt;Valene&amp;#8217;s masterpiece&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc0" name="tocreading-what-to-read" id="tocreading-what-to-read"&gt;Reading what to read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, scouring &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/programming"&gt;proggit&lt;/a&gt; for something worth reading, I found myself &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6rc96/list_of_nontechnical_books_recommended_by_knuth/"&gt;directed&lt;/a&gt; to Don Knuth&amp;#8217;s website and looking at &lt;strong&gt;his&lt;/strong&gt; list of &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/retd.html" title="List of nontechnical books recommended by Don Knuth"&gt;recommended nontechnical books&lt;/a&gt;. Topping this list, to my surprise and delight, I found:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/strong&gt; by Georges Perec (perhaps the greatest 20th century novel).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div class="amazon"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/books/life-a-users-manual.jpg" alt="Life A User's Manual"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knuth may be an expert on sorting but ranking novels by their greatness is an invidious task. Perec&amp;#8217;s masterpiece isn&amp;#8217;t that well-known, in English-speaking countries at least, hence my surprise: few who have read the book would dispute the position claimed for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book visits the rooms of a Parisian apartment block, 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier, on June 23 1978, describing the inhabitants and their stories. There&amp;#8217;s a fascination with detail and lists, with what exactly can be seen in each room, and I&amp;#8217;ll admit this detail perplexed me the first time I read the book &amp;#8212; what could be the significance of all of these &lt;strong&gt;things&lt;/strong&gt;?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On re-reading, I savour the details and the strange patterns they form. Early on, we look at the framed posters hanging on the wall of Madame de Beaumont&amp;#8217;s drawing room.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of [the posters] depicts four greedy-looking monks sitting at a table around a Camembert cheese on the label of which four greedy-looking monks &amp;#8212; the very same &amp;#8212; are again at a table around, etc. The scene is repeated distinctly four times over.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What a wonderful example of visual recursion!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc1" name="tocrecursive-product-packaging" id="tocrecursive-product-packaging"&gt;Recursive product packaging&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve searched shelves and the internet for a good example of recursive product packaging, like the label on the Camembert cheese in the poster, but without much luck&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I felt sure I&amp;#8217;d seen some reflexive cereal boxes. Maybe this kind of visual pun has gone out of fashion?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did find some great &lt;a href="http://www.letyrosemiophile.com/" title="Cheesy site but great labels"&gt;cheese label collections&lt;/a&gt; assembled and put online by dedicated &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=tyrosemiophile"&gt;tyrosemiophiles&lt;/a&gt;. Here&amp;#8217;s a greedy-looking monk. And here&amp;#8217;s a donkey-riding monk holding out a Camembert cheese on the label of which you can just make out a donkey-riding monk, the very same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/camembert-monks.jpg" alt="Camembert labels with monks"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc2" name="tocfractals" id="tocfractals"&gt;Fractals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal" title="Sierpinski Triangle, on Wikipedia"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/45/Sierpinski_triangle.svg/200px-Sierpinski_triangle.svg.png" alt="Sierpinski Triangle"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of mathematics, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal"&gt;fractals&lt;/a&gt; are self-similar shapes. However close you zoom in on them, they look the same. The recursive definition of the Sierpinski triangle is immediately obvious &amp;#8212; it&amp;#8217;s a triangle evenly divided into four Sierpinski triangles. What&amp;#8217;s more remarkable is that the repeating landscapes found in the most &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandelbrot_set"&gt;famous fractal of them all&lt;/a&gt; are revealed by similarly simple mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/G_GBwuYuOOs&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/G_GBwuYuOOs&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc3" name="tocfractals-in-nature" id="tocfractals-in-nature"&gt;Fractals in nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A coastline, for example, continues looks like a coastline as you zoom in on it. Here&amp;#8217;s some self-similar broccoli.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2857208130/" title="Fractal Vegetable by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3149/2857208130_14760d2a1e_m.jpg" width="240" height="180" alt="fractal-vegetable" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc4" name="tocwindows-in-windows" id="tocwindows-in-windows"&gt;Windows in windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point a webcam at a screen which monitors it, and you&amp;#8217;ll see an obvious example of visual recursion. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization software allows you to create a machine within a machine. A host operating system window can display within it a complete graphical user interface for a guest operating system.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would it be possible to take this a level deeper? Using &lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com"&gt;Parallels Desktop&lt;/a&gt; on my OS X host, running Windows XP as a guest, I installed &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com"&gt;VMware Player&lt;/a&gt; virtualization software for Windows. Next I downloaded and started up &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com/appliances/directory/308"&gt;vmTrac&lt;/a&gt;, a 113Mb VMware appliance which packages Trac, Subversion and Lighttpd on a FreeBSD core. The result appears below. I&amp;#8217;ve used Internet Explorer to access Trac, which runs as a web application on FreeBSD, itself running as a Windows XP guest, and Windows XP is a guest on OS X. And I&amp;#8217;m using Google Chrome to display this very article.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2865035348/" title="Windows in Windows by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3023/2865035348_ddfe1b7ed7.jpg" width="500" height="313" alt="windows-in-windows" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc5" name="tocrecursive-paintings-and-prints" id="tocrecursive-paintings-and-prints"&gt;Recursive paintings and prints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fine art world enjoys a tradition of pictures within pictures. &amp;#8220;Circle Limit II&amp;#8221;, a woodcut from the online &lt;a href="http://www.mcescher.com/"&gt;Escher picture gallery&lt;/a&gt;, depicts fishes whose scales are smaller fishes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mcescher.com/Gallery"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.mcescher.com/Gallery/recogn-bmp/LW433.jpg" alt="Circle Limit II"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vel&amp;aacute;zquez&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Meninas"&gt;Las Meninas&lt;/a&gt;, may not be recursive, but it&amp;#8217;s certainly self-referential. We can&amp;#8217;t see the contents of the large canvas in the picture (unless you believe the mirror reflects a portion of it) but the artist working on it is Vel&amp;aacute;zquez himself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Meninas"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/Velazquez-Meninas.jpg/526px-Velazquez-Meninas.jpg" alt="Las Meninas"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc6" name="tocvalenes-masterpiece" id="tocvalenes-masterpiece"&gt;Valene&amp;#8217;s masterpiece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fictional painter, Serge Valene, the longest-standing inhabitant of 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier, narrates &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. Actually, &lt;strong&gt;depicts&lt;/strong&gt; would be a better word, for the book is conceived as a painting showing what would be seen if you removed the facade of the building and peered into each of the rooms. In the central chapter, 51, Valene imagines himself working on just such a painting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;He would be standing beside his almost finished painting, and he would be precisely in the process of painting himself, sketching in with the tip of his brush the minute silhouette of a painter in a long grey smock and a violet scarf, with his palette in his hand, painting again the infinitesimal figurine of a painter painting, once again one of these nested reflections he would have wanted to pursue to infinite depths, as if his eyes and his hand had unlimited magnifying power.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div class="amazon"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;&lt;img src="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/Images/CouvVME2.jpg" alt="Life A User's Manual"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think it spoils the book to tell you he never completes this ambitious canvas. In fact he gets no further than drawing a few charcoal lines, the sketch of a cross-section of the building which no figure, now, will ever inhabit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sketch appears as one of several appendices to the book, annotated with the names of who lived in each room, and when. It may not be finished but it does provide a key to one of the algorithms used to generate the book&amp;#8217;s structure, and, stepping outside the fiction, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;the book&lt;/a&gt; itself is finished and complete.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/"&gt;Word Aligned&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/retd.html" title="List of nontechnical books recommended by Don Knuth"&gt;Knuth&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6rc96/list_of_nontechnical_books_recommended_by_knuth/"&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;)).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;Life, A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/pages/construction.html"&gt;&lt;img src="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/Images/planVME.gif" alt="Knight's tour of 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
   &lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; Update: happily Stephan Schroevers &lt;a href="http://www.haloscan.com/comments/wordaligned/recursive_pictures/#34601"&gt;did rather better&lt;/a&gt;. I should have searched for &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=droste+effect"&gt;&amp;#8220;Droste effect&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=mise+en+abyme"&gt;&amp;#8220;mise en abyme&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The effect is named after a particular image, that appeared, with variations, on the tins and boxes of Droste cocoa powder, one of the main Dutch brands. It displays a nurse carrying a serving tray with a cup of hot chocolate and a box of the same brand. &amp;#8212; &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droste_effect"&gt;The Droste effect, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droste_effect"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/62/Droste.jpg" alt="Droste Cocoa powder"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2008-09-17</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures</link>
<category>Knuth</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
