<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Perec @IgniteSwansea #3</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/docs/ignite/perec/me-at-ignite.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puzzle&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.igniteswansea.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Ignite Swansea #3&lt;/a&gt; I spoke about Georges Perec&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perec was &amp;#8212; and indeed still is &amp;#8212; a member of OuLiPo, a Parisian literary group interested in exploring the effects of applying mathematical patterns to text. His work seemed an appropriate subject for a presentation constrained to fit the ignite formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 slides &amp;times; 15 seconds = 5 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s material I&amp;#8217;ve spoken about &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/tags/perec&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; but &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/docs/ignite/perec/&quot;&gt;the slides are new&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/-y7YOKIa6yQ&quot;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt;. I enjoyed attempting &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just_a_Minute&quot;&gt;just-a-minute&lt;/a&gt; &amp;times; 5, though on the night I could have sworn I was subject to a cruel powerpoint bug which sped up the playback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-y7YOKIa6yQ?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OuLiPo fans might like to see if they can find the clinamen. The moustache is what happens in the fourth week of &lt;a href=&quot;https://uk.movember.com/&quot;&gt;Movember&lt;/a&gt;. My thanks to all &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.igniteswansea.co.uk/&quot;&gt;@IgniteSwansea&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cinemaco.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Cinema &amp;amp; Co&lt;/a&gt; for putting on such a great evening.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2018-02-03</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/perec-igniteswansea-3</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/perec-igniteswansea-3</link>
<category>Perec</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Pay rise please</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In 1967 Georges Perec wrote a radio play, L&amp;#8217;Augmentation, in which you, the protagonist, make some delicate decisions whilst negotiating a pay rise. Is your boss, Mr X, in a good mood? Did he have fish for lunch? Does one of his daughters have measles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/perec-flowchart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flowchart&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story takes the form of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flowchart&quot;&gt;flow chart&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s no coincidence it was written when computers were becoming a part of office and laboratory work, and when flow charts became a popular way to represent the algorithms they were programmed with. 1967 is also the year Perec joined Oulipo, a literary organisation whose members seek to create works based around mathematical constraints and structures. The loops and branches of Perec&amp;#8217;s flow chart perfectly embody the frustrating routines of office politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifty years on, I&amp;#8217;ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wordaligned/pay-rise-please&quot; title=&quot;Pay rise please, on Github&quot;&gt;created a version&lt;/a&gt; to run on Alexa, which you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Mr-Pay-rise-please/dp/B07417SK8N&quot; title=&quot;Pay rise please, on Amazon&quot;&gt;download from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. It may not get me a pay rise, but I should qualify for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.amazon.com/alexa-skills-kit&quot;&gt;freebie Echo Dot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/perec512.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Georges Perec&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-07-25</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/pay-rise-please</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/pay-rise-please</link>
<category>Perec</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Lessons from the OuLiPo</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m delighted to announce that my talk, &lt;a href=&quot;http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2015/accu2015_sessions#lessons_from_the_oulipo&quot;&gt;Lessons from the OuLiPo&lt;/a&gt;, has been accepted for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2015&quot; title=&quot;ACCU 2015 conference&quot;&gt;ACCU 2015 conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/lessons-from-the-oulipo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Slide 1&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk follows up on a lightning talk I gave at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.snsystems.com/&quot; title=&quot;SN Systems website&quot;&gt;my employer&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; last year about Georges Perec&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/knights-tour&quot;&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. Click the graphic below to play the animation and read the transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/knights-tour&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/knights-tour.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Knights tour&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be giving a preview of the full version here in Bristol in a couple of weeks. I hope you can come along. More details on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/ACCU-Bristol/events/219301279/&quot;&gt;Meetup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meanwhile, the next section of this page introduces the ideas I&amp;#8217;ll be exploring in my talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&amp;sect;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As software developers we often ponder what it is we do: are we architects, engineers, or scientists? Are we &amp;#8212; &lt;em&gt;gasp!&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; rock stars or ninjas? Which metaphors best fit? Tending a code base is like gardening. Through the seasons we encourage new growth, whilst pruning back dead code and squashing bugs. Programming is like carpentry, maybe. Select the right tool from a set kept sharp and ready for action. Programming is like cooking. Source the finest ingredients and follow the recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there&amp;#8217;s a more obvious metaphor. Actually there&amp;#8217;s nothing meta- about it. It is what we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;We&amp;#8217;re writers.&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We write to communicate and to instruct. We write for fun and profit. We edit and adapt. We rewrite. We borrow text from other writers. The languages we think we write in &amp;#8212; C++, Python, Javascript &amp;#8212; are actually just highly stylised dialects of our native tongue. Like poets we&amp;#8217;re particular about punctuation and space. We have strange ideas about spelling. The texts we write, &lt;em&gt;programs&lt;/em&gt;, are subject to formal constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;We&amp;#8217;re writers bound by mathematical rules.&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November, 1960. Paris. The poet Raymond Queneau organises the first meeting of a group which will become known as OuLiPo. A dozen turn up: writers, mathematicians, pataphysicians and surrealists. Their mission: to explore the literary potential of applying mathematical constraints to texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course constrained writing is nothing new &amp;#8212; consider the haiku: 17 syllables, arranged as 3 phrases of 5, 7 and 5 syllables, a Japanese form many centuries old &amp;#8212; and one strand of the OuLiPo&amp;#8217;s efforts is devoted to researching past experiments and structures; but I claim it&amp;#8217;s no coincidence the OuLiPo emerged at much the same time as our own novel form of constrained writing: computer programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2015/accu2015_sessions#lessons_from_the_oulipo&quot;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#8217;ll discuss the OuLiPo in more depth, investigating the parallels between their work and ours. We&amp;#8217;ll focus on Georges Perec, whose book &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/knights-tour&quot;&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt; is an Oulipian tour de force. There will be some code, as well as quines, easter eggs and &amp;#8212; as you&amp;#8217;d expect &amp;#8212; bugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2015-01-12</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/lessons-from-the-oulipo</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/lessons-from-the-oulipo</link>
<category>Perec</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Favicon</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;On the subject of &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/&quot;&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to mention the recent addition of a favicon &lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/favicon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Little chap favicon&quot;/&gt;. Per pixel, it&amp;#8217;s cost me more effort than any other feature; but then it&amp;#8217;s accessed more than any other asset. It&amp;#8217;s meant to be a piece from a jigsaw puzzle. I got the idea when &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures.html&quot;&gt;re-reading Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. I like &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/tag/puzzles/&quot;&gt;puzzles&lt;/a&gt; and piecing things together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;amazon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/books/life-a-users-manual.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Life A User&#x27;s Manual&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perec&amp;#8217;s great masterpiece is packed with interwoven stories and trickery, but at its heart is the epic battle between the millionaire, Bartlebooth, and the puzzle-maker Gaspard Winckler. Bartlebooth begins his campaign by learning how to paint, which takes him 10 years. For the next 20 years he travels the world, painting a water colour picture of a different port every couple of weeks. He sends the paintings back home to Paris. On receipt, Winckler glues each picture to a board which he then cuts, making a series of jigsaw puzzles for Bartlebooth to solve on his return. Once Bartlebooth completes each puzzle, an ingenious process is used to glue its pieces together and re-join the cut fibres of the paper; then the picture itself is lifted from the board, returned to the port it depicts, and washed clean in the sea; and finally the paper is returned in something close to its original state to Bartlebooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, after 50 years of work, there will be nothing to show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/jigsaw-fr.png&quot; alt=&quot;French jigsaw pieces&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the book&amp;#8217;s preamble Perec describes familiar die-cut jigsaws, classifying the best known pieces of such puzzles as &amp;#8220;little chaps&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;double crosses&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;crossbars&amp;#8221;. Such diversions are eschewed by the true puzzler:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The art of jigsaw puzzling begins with wooden puzzles cut by hand, whose maker undertakes to ask himself all the questions the player will have to solve, and, instead of allowing chance to cover his tracks, aims to replace it with cunning, trickery and subterfuge. All the elements occurring in the image to be reassembled &amp;#8212; this armchair covered in gold brocade, that three-pointed black hat with its rather ruined black plume, or that silver-braided bright yellow livery &amp;#8212; serve by design as points of departure for trails that lead to false information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thanks to Tim Beard for scanning a couple of pages from his edition of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Vie_mode_d%27emploi&quot; title=&quot;Life A User&#x27;s Manual, Wikipedia&quot;&gt;La Vie, Mode d&amp;#8217;Emploi&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to know what the &amp;#8220;little chaps&amp;#8221; etc. were before they got translated into English. I realise my favicon &lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/favicon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Little chap favicon&quot;/&gt; could be &lt;a href=&quot;http://typophile.com/node/60577&quot; title=&quot;Astonishing exploded view of improved YouTube favicon&quot;&gt;improved&lt;/a&gt; but I don&amp;#8217;t know how to go about it. Anyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://typophile.com/node/60577&quot; title=&quot;YouTube Favicon - improved&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/youtube1.png&quot; width=&quot;52px&quot; height=&quot;26px&quot; alt=&quot;YouTube Favicon - improved&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://typophile.com/node/60577&quot; title=&quot;YouTube Favicon - improved&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/youtube2.png&quot; width=&quot;104px&quot; height=&quot;52px&quot; alt=&quot;YouTube Favicon - improved&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://typophile.com/node/60577&quot; title=&quot;YouTube Favicon - improved&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/youtube3.png&quot; width=&quot;208px&quot; height=&quot;104px&quot; alt=&quot;YouTube Favicon - improved&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-09-16</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/favicon</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/favicon</link>
<category>Perec</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Life, user manuals, recursive pictures</title>
<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-what-to-read&quot;&gt;Reading what to read&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, scouring &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/programming&quot;&gt;proggit&lt;/a&gt; for something worth reading, I found myself &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6rc96/list_of_nontechnical_books_recommended_by_knuth/&quot;&gt;directed&lt;/a&gt; to Don Knuth&amp;#8217;s website and looking at &lt;strong&gt;his&lt;/strong&gt; list of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/retd.html&quot; title=&quot;List of nontechnical books recommended by Don Knuth&quot;&gt;recommended nontechnical books&lt;/a&gt;. Topping this list, to my surprise and delight, I found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/strong&gt; by Georges Perec (perhaps the greatest 20th century novel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;amazon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/books/life-a-users-manual.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Life A User&#x27;s Manual&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knuth may be an expert on sorting but ranking novels by their greatness is an invidious task. Perec&amp;#8217;s masterpiece isn&amp;#8217;t that well-known, in English-speaking countries at least, hence my surprise: few who have read the book would dispute the position claimed for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book visits the rooms of a Parisian apartment block, 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier, on June 23 1978, describing the inhabitants and their stories. There&amp;#8217;s a fascination with detail and lists, with what exactly can be seen in each room, and I&amp;#8217;ll admit this detail perplexed me the first time I read the book &amp;#8212; what could be the significance of all of these &lt;strong&gt;things&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On re-reading, I savour the details and the strange patterns they form. Early on, we look at the framed posters hanging on the wall of Madame de Beaumont&amp;#8217;s drawing room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of [the posters] depicts four greedy-looking monks sitting at a table around a Camembert cheese on the label of which four greedy-looking monks &amp;#8212; the very same &amp;#8212; are again at a table around, etc. The scene is repeated distinctly four times over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a wonderful example of visual recursion!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recursive-product-packaging&quot;&gt;Recursive product packaging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve searched shelves and the internet for a good example of recursive product packaging, like the label on the Camembert cheese in the poster, but without much luck&lt;a id=&quot;fn1link&quot; href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.codeship.com/building-minimal-docker-containers-for-go-applications/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I felt sure I&amp;#8217;d seen some reflexive cereal boxes. Maybe this kind of visual pun has gone out of fashion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did find some great &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.letyrosemiophile.com/&quot; title=&quot;Cheesy site but great labels&quot;&gt;cheese label collections&lt;/a&gt; assembled and put online by dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/search?q=tyrosemiophile&quot;&gt;tyrosemiophiles&lt;/a&gt;. Here&amp;#8217;s a greedy-looking monk. And here&amp;#8217;s a donkey-riding monk holding out a Camembert cheese on the label of which you can just make out a donkey-riding monk, the very same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/images/camembert-monks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camembert labels with monks&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;fractals&quot;&gt;Fractals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal&quot; title=&quot;Sierpinski Triangle, on Wikipedia&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float:right;&quot; src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/45/Sierpinski_triangle.svg/200px-Sierpinski_triangle.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sierpinski Triangle&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of mathematics, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal&quot;&gt;fractals&lt;/a&gt; are self-similar shapes. However close you zoom in on them, they look the same. The recursive definition of the Sierpinski triangle is immediately obvious &amp;#8212; it&amp;#8217;s a triangle evenly divided into four Sierpinski triangles. What&amp;#8217;s more remarkable is that the repeating landscapes found in the most &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandelbrot_set&quot;&gt;famous fractal of them all&lt;/a&gt; are revealed by similarly simple mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;344&quot;&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;movie&quot; value=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/G_GBwuYuOOs&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;allowFullScreen&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/G_GBwuYuOOs&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&quot; type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;344&quot;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fractals-in-nature&quot;&gt;Fractals in nature&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A coastline, for example, continues looks like a coastline as you zoom in on it. Here&amp;#8217;s some self-similar broccoli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2857208130/&quot; title=&quot;Fractal Vegetable by Thomas Guest, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3149/2857208130_14760d2a1e_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;180&quot; alt=&quot;fractal-vegetable&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;windows-in-windows&quot;&gt;Windows in windows&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point a webcam at a screen which monitors it, and you&amp;#8217;ll see an obvious example of visual recursion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization software allows you to create a machine within a machine. A host operating system window can display within it a complete graphical user interface for a guest operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would it be possible to take this a level deeper? Using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.parallels.com&quot;&gt;Parallels Desktop&lt;/a&gt; on my OS X host, running Windows XP as a guest, I installed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vmware.com&quot;&gt;VMware Player&lt;/a&gt; virtualization software for Windows. Next I downloaded and started up &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vmware.com/appliances/directory/308&quot;&gt;vmTrac&lt;/a&gt;, a 113Mb VMware appliance which packages Trac, Subversion and Lighttpd on a FreeBSD core. The result appears below. I&amp;#8217;ve used Internet Explorer to access Trac, which runs as a web application on FreeBSD, itself running as a Windows XP guest, and Windows XP is a guest on OS X. And I&amp;#8217;m using Google Chrome to display this very article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2865035348/&quot; title=&quot;Windows in Windows by Thomas Guest, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3023/2865035348_ddfe1b7ed7.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;313&quot; alt=&quot;windows-in-windows&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recursive-paintings-and-prints&quot;&gt;Recursive paintings and prints&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fine art world enjoys a tradition of pictures within pictures. &amp;#8220;Circle Limit II&amp;#8221;, a woodcut from the online &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mcescher.com/&quot;&gt;Escher picture gallery&lt;/a&gt;, depicts fishes whose scales are smaller fishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mcescher.com/Gallery&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.mcescher.com/Gallery/recogn-bmp/LW433.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Circle Limit II&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vel&amp;aacute;zquez&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Meninas&quot;&gt;Las Meninas&lt;/a&gt;, may not be recursive, but it&amp;#8217;s certainly self-referential. We can&amp;#8217;t see the contents of the large canvas in the picture (unless you believe the mirror reflects a portion of it) but the artist working on it is Vel&amp;aacute;zquez himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Meninas&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/Velazquez-Meninas.jpg/526px-Velazquez-Meninas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Las Meninas&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;valenes-masterpiece&quot;&gt;Valene&amp;#8217;s masterpiece&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fictional painter, Serge Valene, the longest-standing inhabitant of 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier, narrates &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20&quot;&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. Actually, &lt;strong&gt;depicts&lt;/strong&gt; would be a better word, for the book is conceived as a painting showing what would be seen if you removed the facade of the building and peered into each of the rooms. In the central chapter, 51, Valene imagines himself working on just such a painting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He would be standing beside his almost finished painting, and he would be precisely in the process of painting himself, sketching in with the tip of his brush the minute silhouette of a painter in a long grey smock and a violet scarf, with his palette in his hand, painting again the infinitesimal figurine of a painter painting, once again one of these nested reflections he would have wanted to pursue to infinite depths, as if his eyes and his hand had unlimited magnifying power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;amazon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/Images/CouvVME2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Life A User&#x27;s Manual&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think it spoils the book to tell you he never completes this ambitious canvas. In fact he gets no further than drawing a few charcoal lines, the sketch of a cross-section of the building which no figure, now, will ever inhabit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sketch appears as one of several appendices to the book, annotated with the names of who lived in each room, and when. It may not be finished but it does provide a key to one of the algorithms used to generate the book&amp;#8217;s structure, and, stepping outside the fiction, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20&quot;&gt;the book&lt;/a&gt; itself is finished and complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/&quot;&gt;Word Aligned&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/retd.html&quot; title=&quot;List of nontechnical books recommended by Don Knuth&quot;&gt;Knuth&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6rc96/list_of_nontechnical_books_recommended_by_knuth/&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20&quot;&gt;Life, A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/pages/construction.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/Images/planVME.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Knight&#x27;s tour of 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;fn1&quot; href=&quot;http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#fn1link&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.codeship.com/building-minimal-docker-containers-for-go-applications/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Update: happily Stephan Schroevers &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.haloscan.com/comments/wordaligned/recursive_pictures/#34601&quot;&gt;did rather better&lt;/a&gt;. I should have searched for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/search?q=droste+effect&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Droste effect&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/search?q=mise+en+abyme&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;mise en abyme&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect is named after a particular image, that appeared, with variations, on the tins and boxes of Droste cocoa powder, one of the main Dutch brands. It displays a nurse carrying a serving tray with a cup of hot chocolate and a box of the same brand. &amp;#8212; &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droste_effect&quot;&gt;The Droste effect, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droste_effect&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/62/Droste.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Droste Cocoa powder&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2008-09-17</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures</link>
<category>Perec</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
