<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Me, Myself and OpenID</title>
<description>&lt;h3&gt;That&amp;#8217;s not strictly Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pyconuk.org"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.pyconuk.org/images/pyconuk_logo_72x72.png" alt="[PyCon UK]" style="float:right"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the opening day of &lt;a href="http://www.pyconuk.org"&gt;PyCon UK&lt;/a&gt; 2007 &lt;a href="http://simonwillison.net"&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt; delivered a keynote presentation entitled &amp;#8220;Building the Social Web with OpenID&amp;#8221;. Willison is an assured and expert presenter, and it took him just an hour to work through 146 multimedia &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/simon/building-the-social-web-with-openid"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; pitching &lt;a href="http://openid.net"&gt;OpenID&lt;/a&gt; as, in a sentence:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;single sign-on for the web.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time I felt disappointed: I&amp;#8217;d expected something more directly related to Python. Looking back from almost a year on, I realise that the presentation I got most from at that conference also had little directly to do with Python (&lt;a href="http://jon.es/terry.html"&gt;Dr. Terry Jones&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;#8220;Fluidinfo - towards the next everything&amp;#8221;&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/me-myself-and-openid.html#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). For me, conferences are a chance to step back and reflect, to learn about new things, which is why, this year, I chose to attend the more eclectic &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2008"&gt;ACCU 2008 conference&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Viral networks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simon Willison&amp;#8217;s 2007 keynote has turned out to be a slow-burner. I&amp;#8217;m a curmudgeon when it comes to the social web: I didn&amp;#8217;t start instant-messaging until recently, and although I&amp;#8217;ve signed up for FaceSpace, HookdUp! and InKrowd&lt;a id="fn2link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/me-myself-and-openid.html#fn2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I forget why and can&amp;#8217;t claim to get what they&amp;#8217;re about. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my reticence, invitations to join some new social network regularly appear in my inbox, usually from my oldest nephew. He&amp;#8217;s not trying to rescue me; I just happen to be in his address book, and he doesn&amp;#8217;t think twice about handing over the keys to his online identity whenever he signs up to some network. There&amp;#8217;ll be a prompt:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let your friends know you&amp;#8217;ve joined MeeToo!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;All you then have to do is enter your Microyahooglesoft! password and anyone you&amp;#8217;ve ever emailled will receive your invitation to connect; thus the invitations replicate, like a chain letter, but without the expense of copying or postage. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you will have to do, though, and keep doing, is reinvent yourself by claiming a new username and password for every network you join. Inevitably you&amp;#8217;ll recycle passwords. And so your disparate online identities share a common vulnerability.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;OpenID&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://openid.net"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://openid.net/logo-graphics/openid-icon-100x100.png" alt="[OpenID]"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://openid.net"&gt;OpenID&lt;/a&gt; aims to address several problems with this picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     If a website allows you the chance to sign-up using OpenID, you don&amp;#8217;t have to create a new identity to use that site. You don&amp;#8217;t have to trust the site with your credentials at all. Authentication is done off-site by your chosen OpenID provider. Here&amp;#8217;s a short clip in which Simon Willison demonstrates how it works:
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/Vq0R1Y1A2rE&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&amp;amp;color1=0xe1600f&amp;amp;color2=0xfebd01"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/Vq0R1Y1A2rE&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&amp;amp;color1=0xe1600f&amp;amp;color2=0xfebd01" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like all that&amp;#8217;s good about the internet, OpenID is an &lt;a href="http://openid.net/developers/specs/"&gt;open and free standard&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#8217;m hoping this means it really is secure! It also means developers have a choice of &lt;a href="http://wiki.openid.net/Libraries"&gt;implementations&lt;/a&gt; and users have a choice of &lt;a href="http://openid.net/get/"&gt;providers&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The OpenID tagline, &amp;#8220;single sign-on for the web&amp;#8221;, can be misleading. You&amp;#8217;re not limited to a single identity. It&amp;#8217;s perfectly valid to create separate identities for separate roles, just as fiction writers might choose to publish in different genres using different names.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leading blog sites already support OpenID, meaning you can maintain an identity when, e.g., commenting on WordPress, Blogger and LiveJournal blogs.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve noticed an increasing interest in OpenID. More people write about it, more sites offer it. Here&amp;#8217;s a graph on the &lt;a href="http://janrain.com/blog/"&gt;JanRain blog&lt;/a&gt; showing the increase in Unique Relying Parties (sites that accept OpenID).
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://janrain.com/blog/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://janrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/06/image0011.png" alt="[OpenID relying parties]" width="80%"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Mistrust&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for the hype. Software developers have a healthy skepticism for new technologies, as evidenced in &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/blogs/1466"&gt;this article by Alan Lenton&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately the article is weakened by a few misconceptions but the closing paragraph did make me stop and think.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, who would you trust your personal information to? Microsoft? Google? Yahoo? IBM? VeriSign? Not a cat in hell&amp;#8217;s chance!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, an OpenID identifier is just a URL which you can prove you own. If you already own a domain you can use a URL within that domain, and it&amp;#8217;s possible to change your OpenID provider without changing your identity using &lt;a href="http://openid.net/specs/openid-authentication-1_1.html#delegating_authentication"&gt;delegation&lt;/a&gt;. You just add a couple of links to the head of the page at this URL. The OpenID specification shows how an end user would delegate to their LiveJournal account.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="typocode"&gt;

&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;&amp;lt;link rel="openid.server" href="http://www.livejournal.com/openid/server.bml"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;link rel="openid.delegate" href="http://exampleuser.livejournal.com/"&amp;gt;

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple indirection allows you to maintain an identifier while changing providers. With just a little more effort you can &lt;a href="http://wiki.openid.net/Run_your_own_identity_server"&gt;host your own identity server&lt;/a&gt;. Of course there&amp;#8217;s much to be said for using a specialist third party but I wanted to see how easy a do-it-yourself approach could be.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the easiest way turned out to be &lt;a href="http://siege.org/projects/phpMyID/"&gt;phpMyID&lt;/a&gt;, a standalone, single user, OpenID Identity Provider implemented in just two files. One, a configuration file, you edit, supplying your username and a secure hash of your chosen password; the other contains an OpenID implementation in PHP. Upload both files to your webserver. And that&amp;#8217;s it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project &lt;a href="https://www.siege.org/svn/oss/phpMyID/trunk/README"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; is good. In addition, a fine &lt;a href="http://www.intertwingly.net/blog/2007/01/03/OpenID-for-non-SuperUsers"&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Sam Ruby walks through the process, explaining each step and polishing the URLs, and &lt;a href="http://janrain.com"&gt;JanRain&lt;/a&gt; provides a form allowing you to &lt;a href="http://www.openidenabled.com/resources/openid-test/checkup"&gt;check&lt;/a&gt; your OpenID. For the record, my identifier is &lt;code&gt;tag.wordaligned.org&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://lighttpd.net"&gt;lighttpd&lt;/a&gt; server configuration looks like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="typocode"&gt;

&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;$HTTP["host"] == "tag.wordaligned.org" {
    server.document-root = basedir + "self"
    fastcgi.server = (
        ".php" =&amp;gt; ((
            "bin-path" =&amp;gt; "/usr/local/bin/php-cgi",
            "socket" =&amp;gt; basedir + "lighttpd/php.socket"
    ))),
    index-file.names  = ( "index.php", "index.html" )
    ...
}

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Next steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single sign-on for the web is doubly misleading. You can only sign on to those parts of the web which accept OpenID, and that doesn&amp;#8217;t include many of the sites which I&amp;#8217;ve actually bothered signing up for to date. But now that I have an OpenID, I&amp;#8217;ll be using it when I can. Watch this space!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/me-myself-and-openid.html#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; I recommend subscribing to Terry Jones&amp;#8217; &lt;a href="http://www.fluidinfo.com/terry/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;: lots of original, thought-provoking material. &lt;a href="http://simonwillison.net"&gt;Simon Willison&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt; is also an excellent source of material for anyone interested in Web development. You can sign into it using OpenID.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fn2" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/me-myself-and-openid.html#fn2link"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; I invented these site names as silly parodies. It turns out they&amp;#8217;ve all been registered and some are indeed operating social networks.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2008-07-09</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/me-myself-and-openid.html</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/me-myself-and-openid.html</link>
<category>php</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
