<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Perec @IgniteSwansea #3</title>
<description>&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/ignite/perec/me-at-ignite.jpg" alt="Puzzle"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href="http://www.igniteswansea.co.uk/"&gt;Ignite Swansea #3&lt;/a&gt; I spoke about Georges Perec&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perec was &amp;#8212; and indeed still is &amp;#8212; a member of OuLiPo, a Parisian literary group interested in exploring the effects of applying mathematical patterns to text. His work seemed an appropriate subject for a presentation constrained to fit the ignite formula:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;20 slides &amp;times; 15 seconds = 5 minutes
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s material I&amp;#8217;ve spoken about &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/tags/perec"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; but &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/ignite/perec/"&gt;the slides are new&lt;/a&gt;. The talk was &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/-y7YOKIa6yQ"&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt;. I enjoyed attempting &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just_a_Minute"&gt;just-a-minute&lt;/a&gt; &amp;times; 5, though on the night I could have sworn I was subject to a cruel powerpoint bug which sped up the playback.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-y7YOKIa6yQ?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OuLiPo fans might like to see if they can find the clinamen. The moustache is what happens in the fourth week of &lt;a href="https://uk.movember.com/"&gt;Movember&lt;/a&gt;. My thanks to all &lt;a href="http://www.igniteswansea.co.uk/"&gt;@IgniteSwansea&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.cinemaco.co.uk/"&gt;Cinema &amp;amp; Co&lt;/a&gt; for putting on such a great evening.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2018-02-03</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/perec-igniteswansea-3</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/perec-igniteswansea-3</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Computer World</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/37406493811/in/dateposted-friend/" title="The Hitchhiker&amp;#x27;s Guide to the Galaxy"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4371/37406493811_0d17fab6cf.jpg" width="401" height="500" alt="The Hitchhiker&amp;#x27;s Guide to the Galaxy"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Douglas Adams&amp;#8217; &amp;#8220;Hitchhiker&amp;#8217;s Guide to the Galaxy&amp;#8221; tells the story of the two most powerful computers ever made. The first, Deep Thought, was designed to figure out the meaning of Life the Universe and Everything. After 7,500,000 years of processing it came up with the concise but unedifying Ultimate Answer of 42. It then undertook the task of designing its successor, a computer sophisticated enough to calculate the Ultimate Question:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;&amp;#8230; A computer which can calculate the Question to the Ultimate Answer, a computer of such infinite and subtle complexity that organic life itself shall form part of its operational matrix &amp;#8230; Yes! I shall design this computer for you. And I shall name it also unto you. And it shall be called &amp;#8230; The Earth.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I first heard this it seemed ridiculous. Now, almost 40 years on, I&amp;#8217;ve realised it&amp;#8217;s true.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s no longer correct to think of computers as discrete units. Computers have the property that when you connect two of them you get another computer, and so on. The network &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; the computer. The Apple in your hand, the Echo on your shelf, the chip in your &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Scepticism-Inc-Bo-Fowler/dp/009927468X"&gt;shopping trolley&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; all combine to form a global connected device. And as Adams predicted, we ourselves form part of the operating system, constantly feeding data back in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/planet-earth.jpg" alt="Planet Earth"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Douglas Adams&amp;#8217; insight puts software development into perspective. True: we no longer print our product on silicon or ship it in boxes, and yes: we accept &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/why-software-development-isnt-like-construction"&gt;construction&lt;/a&gt; is not the right metaphor, but: nor is production. &lt;a href="http://swanseacon.co.uk/schedule/#session-27"&gt;Professor Dave Snowden&lt;/a&gt; talks about entanglement &amp;#8212; think of a system growing like brambles in a thicket. He emphasises what&amp;#8217;s natural, evolutionary and human. Object oriented design lost out when it narrowed its focus. Remember, people are objects too. The world is our platform.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-09-30</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/computer-world</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/computer-world</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>SwanseaCon 2017</title>
<description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Unit tests, lets get sceptical &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thomasguest"&gt;@thomasguest&lt;/a&gt; was a great end to the morning before lunch &lt;a href="https://t.co/EM4RPAs975"&gt;pic.twitter.com/EM4RPAs975&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; SwanseaCon (@SwanseaCon) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SwanseaCon/status/912361247760404480"&gt;September 25, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m just back from a packed two days at &lt;a href="http://swanseacon.co.uk"&gt;SwanseaCon&lt;/a&gt; and would like to thank the organisers, speakers and participants for making such a welcoming and diverse conference happen right where I live.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, highlights included:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     Professor Dave Snowden&amp;#8217;s erudite and slide-free talk. It was a privilege to listen: although I may not quite have kept up, I will certainly follow up
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Irina Tsyganok&amp;#8217;s sensitive and inspirational presentation on pair-programming
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Lawrence Weetman&amp;#8217;s dishwashing demo &amp;#8212; with three on-stage helpers, no less
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Scott Fulton&amp;#8217;s honest report on some personal agile life lessons
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The venue wasn&amp;#8217;t too shabby either.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/37286571132/in/photostream/" title="The view from SwanseaCon"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4462/37286571132_a5892fe22c_z.jpg" width="640" height="185" alt="The view from SwanseaCon"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having attended a fair few technical conferences, it felt refreshing and important to be part of something a little softer. Software development is about community, communication and culture, and SwanseaCon scored top marks on all three.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, again, thanks!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-09-26</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/swanseacon-2017</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/swanseacon-2017</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Pay rise please</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In 1967 Georges Perec wrote a radio play, L&amp;#8217;Augmentation, in which you, the protagonist, make some delicate decisions whilst negotiating a pay rise. Is your boss, Mr X, in a good mood? Did he have fish for lunch? Does one of his daughters have measles?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/perec-flowchart.jpg" alt="Flowchart"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story takes the form of a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flowchart"&gt;flow chart&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s no coincidence it was written when computers were becoming a part of office and laboratory work, and when flow charts became a popular way to represent the algorithms they were programmed with. 1967 is also the year Perec joined Oulipo, a literary organisation whose members seek to create works based around mathematical constraints and structures. The loops and branches of Perec&amp;#8217;s flow chart perfectly embody the frustrating routines of office politics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifty years on, I&amp;#8217;ve &lt;a href="https://github.com/wordaligned/pay-rise-please" title="Pay rise please, on Github"&gt;created a version&lt;/a&gt; to run on Alexa, which you can &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Mr-Pay-rise-please/dp/B07417SK8N" title="Pay rise please, on Amazon"&gt;download from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. It may not get me a pay rise, but I should qualify for a &lt;a href="https://developer.amazon.com/alexa-skills-kit"&gt;freebie Echo Dot&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/perec512.jpg" alt="Georges Perec"/&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-07-25</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/pay-rise-please</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/pay-rise-please</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Agile at a distance &#x1f44d;</title>
<description>&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocstand-up-meetings" name="toc0" id="toc0"&gt;Stand Up Meetings&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tockanban-board" name="toc1" id="toc1"&gt;Kanban Board&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocpair-programming" name="toc2" id="toc2"&gt;Pair Programming&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocdesign-sessions" name="toc3" id="toc3"&gt;Design Sessions&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocretrospectives" name="toc4" id="toc4"&gt;Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocdemonstrations" name="toc5" id="toc5"&gt;Demonstrations&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toctools" name="toc6" id="toc6"&gt;Tools&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocremote-access-for-all" name="toc7" id="toc7"&gt;Remote access for All&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#tocconclusions" name="toc8" id="toc8"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/we-are-here.jpg" alt="We are here"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m happy to be &lt;a href="https://clinithink.com"&gt;part of a team&lt;/a&gt; which supports remote working. This post collects a few notes on how agile practices fare when people may not be colocated. I don&amp;#8217;t claim what&amp;#8217;s written to be generally true; rather, it&amp;#8217;s specific to me, my team, and how we work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/remote-team.jpg" alt="Remote team"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re by no means entirely distributed. There are seven of us in the engineering team, all UK based. We have a dedicated office space and of the seven, four are office-based and three are remote workers. Office-based staff are free to work from home when it suits. I&amp;#8217;m office-based but work from home around 40% of the time, for example. Remote workers typically visit the office every couple of weeks to attend the sprint ceremonies &amp;#8212; review, retrospective, planning. The rest of the company is more distributed and mobile, comprising product and marketing, medical experts, operations engineers, sales and admin.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/wfh.jpg" alt="WFH"/&gt;

&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc0" name="tocstand-up-meetings" id="tocstand-up-meetings"&gt;Stand Up Meetings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/standup.jpg" alt="Stand up"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stand up meetings work well. We&amp;#8217;re all in the one timezone and our stand up starts promptly at 9:15 and typically lasts 20 minutes. Those in the office gather in a conference room. Remote workers call in. We use GoToMeeting for audio, video and screen share. There&amp;#8217;s a large monitor on the wall and the laptop driving it also functions as a second display. The monitor displays the electronic kanban board showing the current state of the sprint. The laptop screen is for webcam output. A speaker-phone handles audio in the conference room. Those calling in use headsets.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meetings work because they&amp;#8217;re short and to the point. Audio in the conference room is adequate at best, but we work around the limitations with a clear protocol, taking it in turns to speak. Not all home workers use webcams, though most do; and the conference webcam doesn&amp;#8217;t fit everyone who&amp;#8217;s in the meeting room. It &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; better if everyone uses a webcam, but the meeting remains effective even if they don&amp;#8217;t.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meetings work equally well &amp;#8212; better even &amp;#8212; if we don&amp;#8217;t use the conference room and everyone joins the meeting from their desk, whether that&amp;#8217;s at home or in the office. As a result the meeting is more punctual and less of an overhead, since there&amp;#8217;s no fiddling with conference room setup: we all connect in advance and the meeting starts when an organiser opens it. Since we all have good headsets audio is clear, meaning interjections and group discussions are possible: it&amp;#8217;s easier to share a joke.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We call it a &amp;#8220;Daily Share&amp;#8221; rather than &amp;#8220;Stand Up&amp;#8221;, but I still think of it as a stand up meeting and always stand up, whether at home or in the office. It&amp;#8217;s a physical cue I&amp;#8217;m engaged with the meeting and makes a change from sitting down. Other remote workers sit down but are equally engaged.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc1" name="tockanban-board" id="tockanban-board"&gt;Kanban Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned we have a digital Kanban board which provides the primary focus for stand up meetings. We use &lt;a href="https://taiga.io"&gt;Taiga&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s OK. You can see stories. Tasks appear, get assigned, move to the right towards completion. Metrics update.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/taiga.jpg" alt="Taiga"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss having an actual, physical Kanban board. There&amp;#8217;s something agreeably tangible about having real cards with stories written on them by hand. Screens are too flat and print is too bland. Having a board you can walk up to and inspect is good. It&amp;#8217;s satisfying to move cards by hand, or cross them off with a marker pen. These physical actions reinforce the sense of progress in a way the online system fails to match. I also like the fact that a physical board very obviously gets cleared down and rebuilt at the end of every sprint. The work that&amp;#8217;s done is done, and the finished cards can be discarded.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc2" name="tocpair-programming" id="tocpair-programming"&gt;Pair Programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t do a huge amount of pair programming but, oddly, I find this also works well with a remote partner. Indeed, there are some advantages to pairing remotely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, setting up a pairing session isn&amp;#8217;t intrusive. To pair with someone in the office I&amp;#8217;ll approach them in person, which makes it harder for them to say no, or not yet. To pair with a remote colleague, I&amp;#8217;ll send a message; it&amp;#8217;s easier for them to control the right time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say remote pairing what I mean is screen-sharing using Skype. There&amp;#8217;s no dual use of the keyboard and mouse. I&amp;#8217;m aware of software which does allow the computer controls to be fully shared: we aren&amp;#8217;t using it &amp;#8230; yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second advantage to this distributed arrangement is that there&amp;#8217;s no special set up needed to make the desk pair-friendly. You don&amp;#8217;t need a second mouse and keyboard, or any extra space to fit two people round one screen. You don&amp;#8217;t need to shift chairs or mugs. What&amp;#8217;s more, you can include another colleague at any point without fuss.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, for me, it&amp;#8217;s a less intense experience. I&amp;#8217;m in my space, my partner&amp;#8217;s in theirs. We&amp;#8217;re focusing on the screen in front of us and the sound coming through the headset. It&amp;#8217;s concentrated but relaxed. I almost never use the webcam for these sessions &amp;#8212; I find it a distraction. Maybe I&amp;#8217;m saying remote pairing is easier on introverts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/pairing.jpg" alt="Pairing"/&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc3" name="tocdesign-sessions" id="tocdesign-sessions"&gt;Design Sessions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#8217;t found a good way of running design sessions remotely. I miss the interaction and activity of having a group of people working together, and the flexibility of a whiteboard which starts clean and ends up packed with boxes, bubbles and arrows.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc4" name="tocretrospectives" id="tocretrospectives"&gt;Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually run retrospectives for my team. We try and get everyone in for them, as well as for the other sprint changeover activities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a challenge running this particular activity with remote participants. The foundation of a good retrospective is engagement and interaction (though of course all meetings would benefit from such focus). Retrospectives are also energetic and mobile. Stand up, sit down, switch tables: these are all things I get my team doing. We draw pictures, scribble notes on index cards and post-its, pass things round &amp;#8212; activities which remote attendees find hard to follow, let alone participate in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these challenges it has been feasible to include remote attendees in retrospectives. My attitude, though, is that everyone&amp;#8217;s invited in person to the retrospective &amp;#8212; along with the other sprint changeover activities &amp;#8212; and my priority is to make the meeting work for those who are physically present.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, some activities work well with remote attendees. It&amp;#8217;s quite fun to hold pictures up for display to the webcam and see a remote colleague do the same. A &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fishbowl_(conversation)"&gt;goldfish bowl&lt;/a&gt; discussion works very well with remote attendees. I&amp;#8217;ve also been pleased with the way everyone adapts to the challenge of the distributed meeting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final point: it&amp;#8217;s even more important not to let this meeting overrun when you have remote participants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/retro.jpg" alt="Retrospective"/&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc5" name="tocdemonstrations" id="tocdemonstrations"&gt;Demonstrations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, product demonstrations work well for local and remote workers. Again, we use GoToMeeting, and again there&amp;#8217;s a clear protocol &amp;#8212; who&amp;#8217;s talking when. A nice benefit of using GoToMeeting is that the demonstration can be recorded for those who can&amp;#8217;t make the meeting, or would like to replay it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/demo.jpg" alt="Demo"/&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc6" name="toctools" id="toctools"&gt;Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s hardly surprising that a distributed version control system works well for a distributed team. We use &lt;a href="https://about.gitlab.com"&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt; as a front-end and it&amp;#8217;s excellent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;a href="https://slack.com"&gt;slack&lt;/a&gt; for team communications. I&amp;#8217;m surprised how much I like it. I can remember how long it took me to use the most basic emoticons in emails etc, and now I&amp;#8217;m actively searching for the perfect emoji to react with. I&amp;#8217;ve even installed the slack app on my phone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m less keen on Skype. It seems both bossy and needy. However, I do use it for phone calls and screen sharing, and it does a fine job of both.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;#8217;t use of cloud technology, docker etc as much as I&amp;#8217;d like, but we are moving in that direction. I have a hefty laptop which weighs me down on my cycle+train commute.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/tools.jpg" alt="Tools"/&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc7" name="tocremote-access-for-all" id="tocremote-access-for-all"&gt;Remote access for All&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level or ramped access to a building isn&amp;#8217;t just for wheelchair users: parents with baby buggies appreciate it, as do couriers wih trolleys, and people who simply find steps hard going.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width="540px" src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/agile-at-a-distance/access-ramp.jpg" alt="Access"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a working environment which is designed to be remote-friendly works better for everyone. For example, when your stand-up meeting is a hosted session that participants dial in to, it&amp;#8217;s possible to attend even when you&amp;#8217;re neither working from home nor in the office &amp;#8212; as was the case last week when I had to drop my daughter off somewhere just when the meeting was due to start. It&amp;#8217;s also trivial to open the meeting to observers, who can quietly attend from any location without any change to the setup. As already mentioned, meetings can be recorded, so even if you can&amp;#8217;t attend you can play back, and if you did attend you can replay later.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course you need to regulate access to company confidential material: source code, design documents, slack channels etc., but use a modern, hosted solution, with well-defined roles and permissions. Does &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; need to be behind a VPN? Make sure the servers are maximally available with minimal red-tape, whatever the time, wherever the client and and whatever operating system it&amp;#8217;s running. Making remote-friendly decisions with modern infrastructure benefits all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to trust your employees to actually &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; when they&amp;#8217;re working from home, but something&amp;#8217;s wrong if that trust is missing. I worked in one office-based job where the boss &amp;#8212; if he wasn&amp;#8217;t in the office &amp;#8212; would make an excuse to phone in late in the day, ostensibly with a query, but actually just checking we were still there. Years later, it still rankles! If, however, you allow and encourage staff to work from home when it suits, without having to make a formal request, you&amp;#8217;ll find that trust repaid and with interest. I&amp;#8217;m happy to handle a support issue in the evening if I&amp;#8217;m set up to do so at home, especially if my (home) working day has flexed so I can take my son to the dentist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance#toc8" name="tocconclusions" id="tocconclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m happy to be part of a team which supports remote working. Agile practices adapt well to an environment where not everyone is in the office all of the time, though it certainly helps to get together in person sometimes, especially for design sessions, retrospectives and planning. The tools to support a distributed team are improving all the time. Being remote friendly benefits everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-04-14</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/agile-at-a-distance</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Unit Tests Questioned: Reading List</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed &lt;a href="http://swanseasdc.co.uk/events/why-service-oriented-architecture/"&gt;talking about unit testing&lt;/a&gt; last night, and would like to thank &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SwanseaSDC"&gt;Swansea Software Development Community&lt;/a&gt; and especially Viv Richards for organising the event, &lt;a href="https://swansea.techhub.com/"&gt;TechHub&lt;/a&gt; for the venue, and everyone who turned up to listen, ask questions and offer feedback.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Up first &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thomasguest"&gt;@thomasguest&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ssdc?src=hash"&gt;#ssdc&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/4nEqh0ErZr"&gt;pic.twitter.com/4nEqh0ErZr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; SSDC (@SwanseaSDC) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SwanseaSDC/status/826137883341885441"&gt;January 30, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slides are available &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You&amp;#8217;ll find links in the slide deck to the various papers and articles I referenced, but for convenience I&amp;#8217;m listing them here with some notes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gwern.net/docs/1996-hoare.pdf" title="Tony Hoare, How Did Software Get So Reliable Without Proof? (PDF)"&gt;How Did Software Get So Reliable Without Proof?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; by Sir Tony Hoare, published in 1996, is a considered and authoritative paper, in which the author calls into question much of his own research. It&amp;#8217;s not necessary to prove your programs correct, he writes, you can create systems which are both large and reliable using more pragmatic techniques. Since then, his conviction has strengthened. I had the privilege of attending his keynote at &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/europython-2009"&gt;Europython 2009&lt;/a&gt;, when he spoke about the science of computing and the engineering of software (this same talk is available on &lt;a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/tony-hoare-computing-engineering"&gt;InfoQ&lt;/a&gt;). His closing slide stated: One day, software will be the most reliable component of every product which contains it; and software engineering will be the most dependable of all engineering professions.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="http://rbcs-us.com/documents/Why-Most-Unit-Testing-is-Waste.pdf" title="Why Most Unit Testing is Waste (PDF)"&gt;Why Most Unit Testing is Waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; by James O Coplien calls out the unit testing zealots and makes the point that testers should be skeptical.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sqlite.org/testing.html" title="How SQLite Is Tested"&gt;How SQLite Is Tested&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; details what it takes to make bomb-proof software. Most of the tests described are system level tests. It&amp;#8217;s an impressive document which proves that writing tests requires creativity, determination and maybe even a sprinkling of malice.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="https://testing.googleblog.com/2016/05/flaky-tests-at-google-and-how-we.html" title="Flaky Tests at Google and How We Mitigate Them, John Micco"&gt;Flaky Tests at Google and How We Mitigate Them&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; is an honest and all too familiar tale of unreliable tests. However hard you try to eradicate test instabilities, it seems they creep back in at the same rate.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/testing-culture.html" title="Goto Fail, Heartbleed, and Unit Testing Culture"&gt;Goto Fail, Heartbleed, and Unit Testing Culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; argues unit tests would have trapped some notorious bugs in low level security software. It goes on to describe in detail the changing culture of the Google Web Server team, which successfully adopted a test-focused regime. There&amp;#8217;s some good advice on de-flaking, so I hope the author connected with his suffering colleagues.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;a href="https://staff.fnwi.uva.nl/p.vanemdeboas/knuthnote.pdf" title="The correspondence between Donald E. Knuth and Peter van Emde Boas on priority deques during the spring of 1977"&gt;The correspondence between Donald E. Knuth and Peter van Emde Boas on priority deques during the spring of 1977&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/big&gt; provides the background and context of Donald Knuth&amp;#8217;s famous quotation, &amp;#8220;Beware of bugs in the above code; I have only proved it correct, not tried it&amp;#8221;. It&amp;#8217;s a a witty admonition but Donald Knuth isn&amp;#8217;t joking. Don&amp;#8217;t trust code until you&amp;#8217;ve run it. Better, run it repeatedly through automated tests.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-02-01</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned-reading-list</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned-reading-list</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Unit Tests Questioned</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to &lt;a href="http://swanseasdc.co.uk/events/why-service-oriented-architecture/"&gt;talking at TechHub Swansea&lt;/a&gt; at the end of the month on the subject of unit testing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction to the talk is here. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/"&gt;&lt;img width=640 src="http://wordaligned.org/images/unit-tests-questioned.png" alt="Unit Tests Questioned"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk we&amp;#8217;ll consider if unit testing is a good use of our time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not questioning whether &lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt; is important. This slide shows the abstract of &lt;a href="http://www.gwern.net/docs/1996-hoare.pdf" title="(PDF) How did software get so reliable without proof?"&gt;a paper published in 1996 by Tony Hoare&lt;/a&gt;. What he says is that you don&amp;#8217;t need to &lt;strong&gt;prove&lt;/strong&gt; your software works: you can make it so through design and review; by testing; and by good engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=640 src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/images/how-did-software-get-so-reliable.png" alt="How did software get so reliable without proof?"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may no longer seem controversial or novel but maybe it was a surprising thing for Tony Hoare to say. After all, he invented &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quicksort"&gt;quicksort&lt;/a&gt; back in 1959, an algorithm which he &lt;strong&gt;proved&lt;/strong&gt; correct. He also proved how quickly it runs, and that &amp;#8212; in the general case &amp;#8212; it couldn&amp;#8217;t be beaten. Much of Hoare&amp;#8217;s subsequent research was dedicated to proving software works using techniques known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formal_methods" title="Formal Methods (Wikipedia)"&gt;formal methods&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is that you write a formal specification of what your program should do, and then you mathematically verify your code satisfies that specification. Surely nothing less is good enough for software which really is a matter of life and death: a life support system, or a device driver in a nuclear warhead, for example? Actually, no, he says in this paper, there are more pragmatic routes to reliable software.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the idea that you can build reliability via testing may once have seemed radical. It doesn&amp;#8217;t any more. Maybe, though, the conventional modern wisdom that &lt;strong&gt;unit tests&lt;/strong&gt; are a good thing should be questioned.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/images/coplien.jpg" alt="Coplien" /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James O Coplien voices a dissenting opinion in a more recent paper, &lt;a href="http://rbcs-us.com/documents/Why-Most-Unit-Testing-is-Waste.pdf" title="(PDF) Why Most Unit Testing is Waste"&gt;&amp;#8220;Why most unit testing is waste&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s Cope on about!?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is the force of current thinking that even the title of this paper makes it seem like he&amp;#8217;s trolling. Having read the paper carefully, I don&amp;#8217;t think he is. That doesn&amp;#8217;t mean I agree with him, but I agree with his attitude:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a lot of advice, but very little of it is backed either by theory, data, or even a model of why you should believe a given piece of advice. Good testing begs skepticism. Be skeptical of yourself: measure, prove, retry. Be skeptical of me for heaven&amp;#8217;s sake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, this talk will do just that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unit tests: let&amp;#8217;s get skeptical!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-01-21</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Go! Steady. Ready?</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2016/accu2016_sessions#Go!_Steady._Ready?"&gt;talking about Go&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2016"&gt;ACCU 2016 Conference&lt;/a&gt; this Friday. If you&amp;#8217;d like to find out what connects an Easter egg with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eadweard_Muybridge#Stanford_and_horse_gaits"&gt;flying horses&lt;/a&gt; and the runner in the green vest, then come along. Expect live coding, concurrent functions and answers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; import antigravity
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/25883297343/in/dateposted-friend/" title="muybridge-horse"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1707/25883297343_356cc33871.jpg" width="500" height="310" alt="muybridge-horse"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/17301552044/in/datetaken/" title="Tyntesfield 10k 2014"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5449/17301552044_92e033c6d2_z.jpg" width="547" height="640" alt="Tyntesfield 10k 2014"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2016-04-18</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/go-steady-ready</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/go-steady-ready</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Advent of Code</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed solving &lt;a href="http://was.tl"&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s excellent &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; programming puzzles over Christmas last year. The puzzles are nicely themed and the site itself is a delight: lighting up an ascii art Christmas tree, row by row, became an addiction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advent of Code is a series of small programming puzzles for a variety of skill levels. They are self-contained and are just as appropriate for an expert who wants to stay sharp as they are for a beginner who is just learning to code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;First time through, I blasted through all the puzzles using Python, leaning on its standard containers, &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/itertools.html"&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt; and text munging capabilities: &amp;#8220;an expert who wants to stay sharp&amp;#8221;, if you like. Now I&amp;#8217;m tackling the problems again using languages and techniques I&amp;#8217;m less comfortable with: &amp;#8220;a beginner who is just learning to code&amp;#8221;, which I like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second time round is fun, slow and instructive. I&amp;#8217;m posting solutions on &lt;a href="https://github.com/wordaligned/advent-of-code"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/advent-of-code.png" alt="ascii xmas tree" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2016-02-22</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/advent-of-code</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/advent-of-code</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Code Reviews - the rules</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The rule is: no code gets checked in without a review.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s not always easy to get a reviewer to sign off a changelist. Does the code build? In all configurations and on all platforms? Do the tests pass? Are all new code paths covered? Does the commit message describe the change? Does the formatting match the style guide? Does the code match its surroundings? How about documentation, compiler warnings, license requirements?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the change really necessary? Could it have been realised more simply?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly the reviewer&amp;#8217;s task is easier if the task has been &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/programming-paired-and-shared"&gt;paired on&lt;/a&gt;. Small and self-contained changelists are more straightforward. Removing code, too, should be less contentious.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on infrastructure, some checklist items can be automated. Ideally the changelist has already been though CI, for example, ticking the builds-cleanly and passes-its-tests boxes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so what? (So obvious!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s another rule, and one I&amp;#8217;ve not seen written down before.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I review code I might well consider how I would have made the change. That doesn&amp;#8217;t mean I&amp;#8217;ll insist the submitter does things my way. In the absence of &lt;a href="https://blog.golang.org/go-fmt-your-code" title="go fmt your code"&gt;automated formatters&lt;/a&gt; there will be more than one acceptable way to lay out the code. Sometimes there&amp;#8217;s little reason to prefer an explicit loop over an algorithm + lambda combination, or vice-versa. &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/go-for-short-variable-names"&gt;Short names&lt;/a&gt; work for me but not for everyone. It&amp;#8217;s hard to argue against test coverage, but is more always better?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such cases I won&amp;#8217;t try to impose my own style on the changelist. Instead, the question becomes: &lt;strong&gt;does the code match the standards we, as a team, have set&lt;/strong&gt;? Or, &lt;strong&gt;do these changes merit a place in our codebase&lt;/strong&gt;?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a simple principle but not an obvious one. It helps me review fairly and also to learn from others on my team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; more than one way to do it!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2015-08-05</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/code-reviews--the-rules</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/code-reviews--the-rules</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Programming Paired and Shared</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming"&gt;pair program&lt;/a&gt; where I work. Two people, one desk. It can get intense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vim_%28cleaning_product%29"&gt;&lt;img style="align:top" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/vim.jpg" alt="Floor cleaner"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/accidental-emacs"&gt;&lt;img style="align:top" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/gnu.jpg" alt="Emacs"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editor wars claim few casualties &amp;mdash; until an emacs and a vim user are forced to share a keyboard and screen, that is. Anyone for notepad?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing the typing isn&amp;#8217;t why we pair. Where I work we also do code reviews. Whilst pair programming is encouraged, code reviews are mandated: code cannot be checked in until approved by a reviewer. That reviewer could be the person you paired with, and it soon becomes apparent that reviews conducted with a pair go more smoothly than ones where the reviewer is new to the task. It&amp;#8217;s hard for someone to review a tricky changeset without the context of its development.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;context of its development&lt;/strong&gt; turns out to be paramount for understanding a codebase, not just a changeset. Pair programming helps provide that context.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;pairing&lt;/strong&gt; serves better than &lt;strong&gt;pair programming&lt;/strong&gt;. The former suggests sharing; the latter, typing. The benefits come from sharing all aspects of the work: decisions and responsibility; research, design, development; how to test; where to cut corners and where to go beyond the immediate requirement; when to take a break. Anyone for table football?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.snsystems.com/careers/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/table-football.jpg" alt="Edd and Bridget vs Bridget and Edd" title="Edd and Bridget kicking a ball around" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2015-05-27</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/programming-paired-and-shared</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/programming-paired-and-shared</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Election Manifesto - a timely activity for agile retrospectives</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Did I mention that I&amp;#8217;ve become scrum master for my team? I have now. It&amp;#8217;s a new thing for me (and for this blog) but I enjoy it, especially running the retrospective meetings. You have to keep these fresh and one way of doing this is to connect them with what&amp;#8217;s going on in the world outside: the &lt;a href="http://plans-for-retrospectives.com/?id=54" title="Story Oscars, a retromat activity"&gt;Oscars&lt;/a&gt;, the eclipse, the &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/election/2015"&gt;general election&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin:0;text-align:center;font-size:800%;"&gt;&amp;#x2611;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a week to go, my vote has been posted. So, here&amp;#8217;s an activity I devised for a recent retrospective. We were focusing on infrastructure issues and trying to come with improvements. For this, it worked well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ask the team to split into three or four &amp;#8220;political&amp;#8221; parties. Each party must come up with a manifesto for change. What isn&amp;#8217;t working? How would they improve things, given the chance? After 20 minutes of discussion, reconvene and ask the party leaders to present their manifesto to the electorate. Be prepared for tough questions and heckling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;#8217;s time to plan a brighter future. Summarise the key points of each manifesto and write them up on sticky notes, using different colours for the different parties. What do the parties agree on? Which promises are unrealistic and which can be delivered?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style="margin:0;text-align:center;font-size:800%;"&gt;&amp;#x2611;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more retrospective ideas, I recommend &lt;a href="http://plans-for-retrospectives.com" title="Retromat, plans for retrospectives"&gt;Retromat&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/findingmarbles" title="@findingmarbles"&gt;Corinna Baldauf&lt;/a&gt;. You can find another suggestion of mine, &lt;a href="http://plans-for-retrospectives.com/?id=97"&gt;#tweetmysprint&lt;/a&gt;, on the Retromat and I&amp;#8217;ve submitted this one too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin:0;text-align:center;font-size:800%;"&gt;&amp;#x2611;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/tweetmysprint?src=hash"&gt;#tweetmysprint&lt;/a&gt; Please write 3 tweets describing this sprint. Stories, suggestions, rants all welcome &amp;mdash; but be brief ;-)&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Professor Scrum (@professorscrum) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/professorscrum/status/583018772891639808"&gt;March 31, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2015-04-29</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/election-manifesto</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/election-manifesto</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Speaking at the ACCU Conference 2015</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This time last week I was on my way to the &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2015" title="ACCU 2015 main page"&gt;ACCU 2015 conference&lt;/a&gt; in Bristol. The past couple of years I&amp;#8217;ve been, but for one day only. This year, as a presenter of a full length (90 minute!) session I got to go to the whole thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a speaker made all the difference. Having the chance to attend plenty of sessions meant I was more relaxed about choosing which ones to pick &amp;#8212; each slot during the day offered &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences/accu_conference_2015/accu2015_schedule" title="ACCU 2015 Schedule"&gt;5 options&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; and less upset if I thought, 10 minutes into a presentation, that I could have picked something else. Perhaps as a consequence of this, I was happy with all my choices. That said, I&amp;#8217;d love the whole thing to run again so I could take a second route through the schedule.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have no idea what &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thomasguest"&gt;@thomasguest&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquot;s &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/accu2015?src=hash"&gt;#accu2015&lt;/a&gt; talk will be about, which is why I&amp;rsquot;m here. &amp;ldqou;Lessons from the OuLiPo&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="http://t.co/l6CKhCBJ7f"&gt;pic.twitter.com/l6CKhCBJ7f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Robert Smallshire (@robsmallshire) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/robsmallshire/status/591256120783728640"&gt;April 23, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d run a couple of practice versions of my talk at ACCU local groups in &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/ACCU-Bristol"&gt;Bristol&lt;/a&gt; and then in &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/ACCU-Oxford"&gt;Oxford&lt;/a&gt;, which meant I was comfortable with the material and convinced it would hold an audience&amp;#8217;s interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beautiful talk by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thomasguest"&gt;@thomasguest&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/accu2015?src=hash"&gt;#accu2015&lt;/a&gt; on adopting artificial constraints in design and programming guided by the OuLiPo.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Robert Smallshire (@robsmallshire) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/robsmallshire/status/591264421470666752"&gt;April 23, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to consider for next year:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     I&amp;#8217;m going to submit another talk proposal, and if it&amp;#8217;s accepted
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     I&amp;#8217;ll practise it twice, at least and
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     I&amp;#8217;ll get a remote control.
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     My laptop is too bulky for comfort. &lt;a href="https://www.themobilepresenter.com/"&gt;Dirk Haun&lt;/a&gt; ran &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/dhaun/braindump-how-to-leave-your-knowledge-when-leaving-your-job"&gt;his talk&lt;/a&gt; from a tablet. Could a phone be used?
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My lightning talk &amp;#9758; &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/knights-tour" title="Perhaps the greatest 20th century novel &amp;amp;mdash; Donald Knuth"&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides for my main talk &amp;#9758; &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/oulipo/"&gt;Lessons from the OuLiPo&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank all the organisers of the conference, everyone who presented, and everyone who attended. Especial mention to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jonjagger" title="Loves people; software; fishing; built http://cyber-dojo.org"&gt;Jon Jagger&lt;/a&gt; who announced that this would be his last year as conference chair. Let&amp;#8217;s hope that in future years the mail bag continues to be inundated with letters! &lt;a href="http://www.goodliffe.net/"&gt;Pete Goodliffe&lt;/a&gt; too deserves a special mention for setting up three excellent lightning talk sessions. Controlled anarchy &amp;mdash; he&amp;#8217;s good at it!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2015-04-28</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/speaking-at-the-accu-conference-2015</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/speaking-at-the-accu-conference-2015</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Word Aligned, hosted by Github</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;To anyone who subscribes to this site&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt;, my apologies if your reader recently got filled with items you&amp;#8217;d already seen. I can explain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About seven years ago, I signed up for a great deal on hosting for life with a company called &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/hosting-for-life-textdrive-revived.html"&gt;TextDrive&lt;/a&gt;. For most of the time since then, this service was actually provided by Joyent &amp;#8212; who took over TextDrive. Then they, Joyent, said the hosting for life deal was being &amp;#8220;sunsetted&amp;#8221;, i.e. canned. Happily TextDrive&amp;#8217;s original founder, Dean Allen, stepped in to revive his company and honour the original offer, which has indeed happened, though it&amp;#8217;s been all too clear that he&amp;#8217;s been hard to get hold of whilst the operations staff have been over-stretched.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, a tweet from one of these hardworking ops tipped me off that TextDrive would soon be gone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public Service Announcement: TextDrivers please note that TextDrive is ceasing operation on the 14th of March 2014  &lt;a href="http://t.co/AMIO3xS2wX"&gt;http://t.co/AMIO3xS2wX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jacques Marneweck (@txdjm) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/txdjm/statuses/441774463386800129"&gt;March 7, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to do?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=static+website+hosting"&gt;googling&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve chosen &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; as the new host for Word Aligned. I&amp;#8217;ve had to relinquish a little control over URLs to make the site truly static. (A side-effect being old content appearing with new identifiers in the RSS &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt;). I also won&amp;#8217;t be configuring a web server or rooting around in rotating log files. The experts at Github can take care of that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do get to keep my own domain, which was paramount. I don&amp;#8217;t have to pay anything, which is nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, I used version control to track my site&amp;#8217;s contents and &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;SSH&lt;/code&gt; to publish. Now I simply use version control: pushing a change to &lt;a href="https://github.com/wordaligned"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; publication.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s early days yet, but I&amp;#8217;m happy with the change. The &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt; should settle down now, so stay subscribed. Please &lt;a href="mailto:tag@wordaligned.org?subject=Wordaligned.org%20glitches"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt; if you spot any problems with the site.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2014-03-13</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/word-aligned-hosted-by-github</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/word-aligned-hosted-by-github</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Patience Sorted</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a lightning talk today about patience sorting and its application to the longest increasing subsequence problem. It&amp;#8217;s a subject I&amp;#8217;ve &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/patience-sort.html" title="Patience sort and the longest increasing subsequence"&gt;written about&lt;/a&gt; before. My computer has been put through several million simulations. I&amp;#8217;ve even coded up a &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/pages/psort"&gt;javascript demo&lt;/a&gt; which deals out virtual playing cards and sorts them at the click of a button.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.3.1/jquery.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
var zz = 0;

var xtop  = ["330px", "302px", "275px", "255px", "234px", "209px", "187px", "158px", "128px", "99px", "70px", "43px", "15px"];
var ytop  = ["26px", "30px", "28px", "29px", "31px", "28px", "27px", "28px", "28px", "30px", "26px", "30px", "29px"];
var xpile = ["10px", "13px", "12px", "115px", "14px", "220px", "220px", "319px", "15px", "216px", "118px", "118px", "321px"];
var ypile = ["205px", "233px", "266px", "206px", "295px", "206px", "236px", "209px", "325px", "267px", "235px", "263px", "234px"];
var result = ["#card7", "#card6", "#card3", "#card2"];

function reset_cards() {
    jQuery("img").stop();
    zz += 13;
    for (var j = 0; j != 13; ++j, --zz) {
        jQuery("#card" + j)
        .css({"z-index":zz, "margin-left":xtop[j], "margin-top":ytop[j], "border-width":0});
    }
    zz += 13;
}

function lis(j) {
    var it = jQuery(result[j]);
    if (it.length &gt; 0) {
        it.animate({borderWidth : "5px"}, "slow", 0, function(){lis(++j);});
    }
}

function psort(j) {
    var it = jQuery("#card"+j);
    if (it.length != 0) {
        it
        .animate({marginLeft : xpile[j], marginTop: ypile[j]}, "slow", 0, function(){psort(++j);})
        .css({"z-index" : ++zz});
    } else {
        lis(0);
    }
}

function animate_cards() {
    reset_cards();
    psort(0);
}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class="cardtable" style="background-color: #093; width:440px; height:480px;"&gt;
&lt;img id="card0" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 330px; margin-top: 27px; z-index: 13;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/1s.png" alt="Ace of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card1" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 302px; margin-top: 27px; z-index: 12;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/10s.png" alt="10 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card2" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 275px; margin-top: 27px; z-index: 11;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/6s.png" alt="6 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card3" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 255px; margin-top: 26px; z-index: 10;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/7s.png" alt="7 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card4" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 234px; margin-top: 28px; z-index: 9;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/5s.png" alt="5 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card5" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 209px; margin-top: 26px; z-index: 8;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/13s.png" alt="King of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card6" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 187px; margin-top: 31px; z-index: 7;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/9s.png" alt="9 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card7" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 158px; margin-top: 27px; z-index: 6;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/12s.png" alt="Queen of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card8" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 128px; margin-top: 29px; z-index: 5;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/2s.png" alt="2 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card9" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 99px; margin-top: 29px; z-index: 4;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/8s.png" alt="8 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card10" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 70px; margin-top: 26px; z-index: 3;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/4s.png" alt="4 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card11" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 43px; margin-top: 27px; z-index: 2;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/3s.png" alt="3 of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;img id="card12" style="border: 0 orange solid; position: absolute; margin-left: 15px; margin-top: 28px; z-index: 1;" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/cards/11s.png" alt="Knave of Spades"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;button onclick="reset_cards();"&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;&lt;button onclick="animate_cards();"&gt;Play&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I used real playing cards; a linen-finished standard deck. For any talk it&amp;#8217;s nice to have a prop.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/8558343442/" title="Rock &amp;amp; Pop Legends by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8100/8558343442_0402f04e83.jpg" width="500" height="361" alt="Rock &amp;amp; Pop Legends"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I &lt;strong&gt;thought&lt;/strong&gt; I understood the patience sort algorithm but until yesterday I&amp;#8217;d never actually played it with real cards. I&amp;#8217;ve been surprised by how much this physical dimension has developed my understanding.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be testing my new cards on some other sorting algorithms; I have high hopes. It would be good to find a similarly simple prop for linked data structures so I can balance trees, flip lists and walk graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2013-03-14</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/patience-sorted</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/patience-sorted</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Hosting for Life? TextDrive revived!</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of last year I was emailed by Jason Hoffman from Joyent. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joyent" title="Wikipedia on Joyent and TextDrive"&gt;Joyent owned TextDrive&lt;/a&gt;, the company which, 6 years ago, offered web hosting &lt;strong&gt;for life&lt;/strong&gt; in return for a single up-front payment. Jason&amp;#8217;s email said this lifetime hosting &amp;#8212; legacy service, he called it &amp;#8212; was nearing &lt;strong&gt;End of Life&lt;/strong&gt; (!) and would be sunsetted (!!) at the end of October 2012.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://textdrive.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/txd-banner.png" alt="TextDrive banner"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a TextDrive customer I reckon I&amp;#8217;d had good value from the original deal, but while six years may seem like forever on the internet it&amp;#8217;s surely not a lifetime. Happily TextDrive&amp;#8217;s original founder, Dean Allen, &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/08/30/happy-ending-to-the-joyent-lifetime-subscription-story/" title="TechCrunch reports on Joyent/TextDrive"&gt;felt the same way&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;he&lt;/strong&gt; emailed me to say he&amp;#8217;d be relaunching &lt;a href="http://textdrive.com/"&gt;TextDrive&lt;/a&gt; on a new, modern, infrastructure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite how this pans out remains to be seen but I&amp;#8217;m sticking it out. If you&amp;#8217;re reading this page, great: it&amp;#8217;s been served up by the new, modern infrastructure which Dean mentioned. Whilst migrating &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/"&gt;wordaligned.org&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve had to fiddle with rewrite rules and tinker with DNS records and file permissions. Any glitches or oddities, please &lt;a href="mailto:tag@wordaligned.org?subject=Wordaligned.org%20glitches"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2013-03-06</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/hosting-for-life-textdrive-revived</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/hosting-for-life-textdrive-revived</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>ACCU Bristol and Bath</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Lightning talks. In a pub. Me first! I hadn&amp;#8217;t actually practised but I knew what I wanted to say and had picked a subject so trivial I couldn&amp;#8217;t possibly overrun.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it was time, at last, for the first &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/accuBristol" title="Follow ACCU Bristol &amp;amp; Bath on twitter"&gt;ACCU Bristol &amp;amp; Bath&lt;/a&gt; meeting, to be held in an upstairs room at the Cornubia. We&amp;#8217;d reconnoitred the venue a few weeks earlier. Although the room was dingy and we couldn&amp;#8217;t work out where to put a screen, and despite disturbance from the increasingly raucous CAMRA meeting next door, the location was ideal and the beer superb. I looked forward to returning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plans change. In an agile last minute switch the meeting relocated to the Marriot &amp;#8212; which, coincidentally, had just been announced as the host of next year&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/conferences" title="ACCU 2013 comes to Bristol!"&gt;ACCU conference&lt;/a&gt;. I shuffled through revolving doors into the hotel&amp;#8217;s vacant lobby rehearsing my talk in my head. Where was everyone? It took some backtracking and interrogation to locate the subterranean room but fortunately they hadn&amp;#8217;t started without me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now &lt;strong&gt;this&lt;/strong&gt; was a proper meeting room. Panelled walls, no windows. A blank TV screen; green apples; red glasses; bottled water.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/apple-display-adapter.jpg" alt="I carry one with me at all times"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ewan welcomed me. &amp;#8220;Have you got a macbook display adapter?&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. I didn&amp;#8217;t even have the slides to my own presentation &amp;#8212; I&amp;#8217;d emailed them ahead to be merged into a single deck.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screen flicked to life. Nine talks, five minutes each. We&amp;#8217;d be done in an hour. After a brief welcome my slides were on screen and I was off.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I ran out of time, laughing too long at my own lightning anecdote which framed a talk about ellipses, the triple-dots &amp;#8230; which mean different things in different places in different programming languages. Next up was Dan Towner who walked us through the algorithm used by compilers for allocating registers. It&amp;#8217;s a greedy colouring of a planar map, he said, wrapped in a bail-and-retry loop. Dan Tallis spoke about the single committer model which works so well on open source projects. Developers don&amp;#8217;t have write access to the repository and must submit patches to the committer for review, a protocol which encourages incremental and considered changes to a codebase. &lt;a href="http://curbralan.com"&gt;Kevlin Henney&lt;/a&gt; needed just a single slide to clear up some misconceptions in exactly five minutes. Chris Simons didn&amp;#8217;t need any slides to describe where designs come from. Pacing the floor and waving his fingers, he explained that &lt;span /&gt;computer systems are punchlines; design is a matter of figuring out the joke. Attack the solution space with ants! No ACCU meeting would be complete without a discourse on C++ test frameworks and Malcolm Noyes duly dazzled us developing a C++ mocking library before our very eyes. Jim Thomson compared before and after binaries to prove his source code rearrangements hadn&amp;#8217;t caused any damage. Ewan Milne, who&amp;#8217;d not only organised and chaired the meeting, also contributed a talk on (guess what?) planning, subtitled how agile can Kanban be (say it!)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.jaggersoft.com"&gt;Jon Jagger&lt;/a&gt; postponed his closing talk. Macs just work if you&amp;#8217;ve got the right connectors. We hadn&amp;#8217;t. The audience wanted more but that&amp;#8217;s no bad thing. We regathered in the hotel bar to crunch apples and chew over the evening. The ACCU Bristol &amp;amp; Bath launch had been a success! The price of a pint and anodyne surroundings discouraged lingering. We drank up and headed off towards trains, homes, and, for a select few, the &lt;a href="http://www.travelswithbeer.com/2010/07/09/the-cornubia-bristol/" title="CAMRA members can get pints at a reduced prices depending on the strength of the ale"&gt;Cornubia&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2012-08-31</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/accu-bristol-and-bath</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/accu-bristol-and-bath</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Life on Canvas</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be taught maths by &lt;a href="http://www.math.princeton.edu/directory/john-conway" title="John Conway, now at Princeton University"&gt;John Horton Conway&lt;/a&gt;, if only for an hour a week for a single term. He was lucky enough to be teaching number theory: a subject packed with treasures picked from the full history of mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember him as animated and unkempt. He bustled into that first lecture with a carrier bag and started pulling out groceries one by one. How many items were in the bag, he wondered? Could he count them all &amp;#8212; it was a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; large bag &amp;#8212; and what exactly did &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Aleph-0.html" title="The 'small' infinite set of integers"&gt;infinity&lt;/a&gt; mean? Later I would see him pacing along Kings Parade dragging a shopping tolley, lost in thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Number theory may be as old as mathematics but it remains very much alive. Some 40 years ago Professor Conway discovered a primitive and novel mathematical life form: the Game of Life. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules are simple. A colony of cells inhabits a two dimensional grid. At any one time each cell is either alive or dead, and as time advances the fate of a cell is determined entirely by its immediate 8 neighbours:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     reproduction: a dead cell with exactly 3 live neighbours becomes alive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     survival: a live cell with 2 or 3 live neighbours lives on
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     overcrowding or loneliness: in all other cases the cell dies or stays dead
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In code, we might represent the colony as a two dimensional array filled with &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#8217;s and &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#8217;s for live and dead cells and code up the rules like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="typocode"&gt;

&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;// Determine the fate of cell i, j in the next generation.
// Return 1 for "lives", 0 for "dies"
function fate(cells, i, j) {
    var neighbours = [[-1,-1],[-1,0],[-1,1],
                      [0,-1],        [0,1],
                      [1,-1], [1,0], [1,1]];
        live_neighbours = 0;
    neighbours.forEach(function(n) { 
        live_neighbours += cells[i + n[0]][j + n[1]];
    });
    return (live_neighbours == 3 || 
            cells[i][j] == 1 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; live_neighbours == 2) ? 1 : 0;
}

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out these simple rules generate an astonishing ecosystem. Simple patterns flourish, evolving into complex patterns which, many generations later may decay into stable forms and repeating patterns, or, occasionally, become extinct. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can a finite pattern grow indefinitely? Conway originally conjectured no, this was impossible, offering $50 to the first person who could prove or disprove the his conjecture before the end of 1970. In November of that year a team from MIT led by Bill Gosper claimed the prize, disproving the conjecture with a glider gun pattern which spits out a new spaceship every 30 generations.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e5/Gospers_glider_gun.gif alt="Gosper's glider gun, Wikimedia commons" style="border:1px solid black;"&gt;

&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2 dimensional array can naturally be represented on the most basic computer screen &amp;#8212; think raster graphics, pixels &amp;#8212; and the parallel emergence and development of the personal computer helps explain life&amp;#8217;s continuing appeal&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/life-on-canvas#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The game of life has become the &lt;a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/Learn_to_Say_%22Hello%2C_World%22" title="Laern to say Hello, world"&gt;hello world&lt;/a&gt; of graphics frameworks. In 2012 we can use the HTML5 canvas, a 2 dimensional surface for drawing on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;canvas id="lifecanvas" width="480" height="320" style="border:1px solid black;"&gt;Unfortunately your client does not support the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html5/the-canvas-element.html#the-canvas-element"&gt;HTML5 canvas element&lt;/a&gt;. If you are using a feed reader, try visiting the &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/life-on-canvas.html"&gt;original page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/canvas&gt;
   &lt;div&gt;
   &lt;button type="button" id="random" title="Random pattern" style="vertical-align:top;width:50px;height:50px;"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/glyphicons_322_playing_dices.png" /&gt;&lt;/button&gt;
   &lt;button type="button" id="clear" title="Clear screen" style="vertical-align:top;width:50px;height:50px;"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/glyphicons_192_circle_remove.png" /&gt;&lt;/button&gt;
   &lt;button type="button" id="toggle" title="Play/Pause" style="vertical-align:top;width:50px;height:50px;"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/glyphicons_174_pause.png" /&gt;&lt;/button&gt;
   &lt;button type="button" id="step" title="Single step" style="vertical-align:top;width:50px;height:50px;"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/glyphicons_178_step_forward.png" /&gt;&lt;/button&gt;
   &lt;button type="button" id="info" title="Help" style="vertical-align:top;width:50px;height:50px;"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/glyphicons_195_circle_info.png" /&gt;&lt;/button&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.7.2/jquery.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
   &lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://wordaligned.org/scripts/simple-life.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a little experimentation you&amp;#8217;re sure to uncover life&amp;#8217;s three main domains: still lives, which remain unchanged; oscillators, which repeat; and spaceships, which move across the board. Then there are methuselahs, puffers, guns &amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a pulsar, an oscillator with period 3.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/pulsar.gif" alt="Pulsar"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;#8217;s a glider, classed as a diagonal spaceship, &lt;a href="http://www.catb.org/hacker-emblem/" title="When you put the glider emblem on your web page, or wear it on clothing, or display it in some other way, you are visibly associating yourself with the hacker culture"&gt;a pattern chosen&lt;/a&gt; by Eric S Raymond as a hackers&amp;#8217; emblem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/glider.gif" alt="Glider, an orthogonal spaceship"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s another 5 cell pattern &amp;#8212; the R-pentomino. Clear the canvas, pick out an R-pentomino cluster of cells with the mouse, click play, and watch what evolves!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/Rpentomino.png" alt="Rpentomino"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.conwaylife.com/wiki/Turtle" title="An orthogonal c/3 spaceship"&gt;Turtle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.conwaylife.com/wiki/Garden_of_Eden" title="A pattern that has no parents and thus can only occur in generation 0"&gt;garden&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.conwaylife.com/wiki/Unicycle" title="Unicycle is a period 6 oscillator made up of four copies of unix"&gt;unicycle&lt;/a&gt;: animal, vegetable, mineral. The kingdom of life is inclusive and extensive, a delight for naturalists and taxonomists alike. It&amp;#8217;s seduced logophiles and lexicographers too: reading through Stephen A. Silver&amp;#8217;s comprehensive &lt;a href="http://www.argentum.freeserve.co.uk/lex.htm" title="A lexicon of terms relating to John Horton Conway's Game of Life, by Stephen Silver"&gt;Life Lexicon&lt;/a&gt;, I learned that an anteater consumes ants, a &lt;a href="http://www.argentum.freeserve.co.uk/lex_c.htm#caterpillar"&gt;caterpillar&lt;/a&gt; works by laying tracks at its front end, a baker&amp;#8217;s dozen is a loaf &lt;a href="http://www.argentum.freeserve.co.uk/lex_h.htm#hassler"&gt;hassled&lt;/a&gt; by two blocks and two caterers, and an &lt;a href="http://www.argentum.freeserve.co.uk/lex_a.htm#ak47reaction"&gt;AK47&lt;/a&gt; reaction occurs when a honey farm predecessor, catalysed by an eater and a block, reappears at another location 47 generations later, having produced a glider and a traffic light. I could go on&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/life-on-canvas#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;: I&amp;#8217;m glossing over details here. The true game of life is played out on an infinite grid, and patterns such as &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gun_(cellular_automaton)"&gt;Gosper&amp;#8217;s glider gun&lt;/a&gt; show that it really does have to be infinite. Computers have trouble with such an unconstrained requirement, and a computer animation might try and adapt the screen as the pattern grows, or limit the region of interest. Another approach is to wrap the canvas, left to right, top to bottom, so the game of life is played out on what&amp;#8217;s topologically a toriodal surface. That&amp;#8217;s what the canvas shown here does.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align:center"&gt;&amp;sect;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The icons used on this page were downloaded from &lt;a href="http://glyphicons.com"&gt;http://glyphicons.com&lt;/a&gt; and are licensed under the &lt;a href=http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en&gt;CC BY 3.0&lt;/a&gt; terms. The animated gifs were placed in the public domain by their authors.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2012-06-27</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/life-on-canvas</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/life-on-canvas</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Desktop preferences</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Paul grumbled about the lack of new content on &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org" title="Once popular, now dormant programming blog"&gt;wordaligned.org&lt;/a&gt; and since he&amp;#8217;d just bought me lunch I thought I&amp;#8217;d better do something about it. He also said he didn&amp;#8217;t like the stuff about &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/tag/algorithms/" title="Wordaligned articles about algorithms"&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt; and maths. Well, that makes my life easier too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m moving jobs &amp;#8212; the &lt;a href="http://www.wagamama.com/locations/showlocation/555/" title="Yaki Udon, fat noodles, filling"&gt;lunch&lt;/a&gt; he paid for was a leaving do &amp;#8212; and my employers kindly allowed me to buy this macbook pro at a reasonable price. Of course I had to wipe and reinstall it. It took an hour and a half to fill the hard drive with zeros and a similar amount of time to load a few ones back on&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/desktop-preferences#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/07/Itchyscratchy.png" alt="Itchy" /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installation done, I set about customisation. The official term is &lt;a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT2490" title="Set your preferences"&gt;preferences&lt;/a&gt; but &lt;strong&gt;annoyances&lt;/strong&gt; would be more accurate: you fix things which irk you before they cause real pain or, worse, you become immune to them. Typing hurt until I set key repeat to the max. Thomas Guest&amp;#8217;s macbook pro is a lousy name. I&amp;#8217;ve used &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/oberon-cromarty-lisa-waggledance-ariel.html" title="Computer names"&gt;Itchy&lt;/a&gt; before and I like it so I&amp;#8217;m using it again. I booted Safari off the dock and stood Chrome in its place. I undocked some other things which I didn&amp;#8217;t recognise by their icons and were obviously of no use to me. By now I&amp;#8217;d seen the galactic login backdrop too many times. I&amp;#8217;ve never found a customisable preference for it but &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=os+x+change+login+background" title="2nd hit worked for me"&gt;google&lt;/a&gt; told me what to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="typocode"&gt;

&lt;pre class="prettyprint"&gt;$ sudo cp Downloads/matt-burns-pylon.jpg \
          /System/Library/CoreServices/DefaultDesktop.jpg

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/floater81/4433735546/" title="IMG_3738 by mattburns.co.uk, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm5.staticflickr.com/4050/4433735546_42b2bf1ce7.jpg" width="500" height="333" alt="IMG_3738"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, that&amp;#8217;s pretty much all I needed to fix. Now it really was about preferences I prefer. Aquamacs. Skype. I chose two pictures for my desktop backgrounds. What you want on a desktop &amp;#8212; no, what &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; want on &lt;strong&gt;my&lt;/strong&gt; desktop &amp;#8212; is something gorgeous but not distracting, something personal but not too personal, something which works in widescreen, something of a &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/rbrwr/308905101" title="Too grainy for my desktop"&gt;high enough resolution&lt;/a&gt;, something which &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/5017113982" title="Which sadly rules out this picture, my favourite of the sketches I made at Bristol museum"&gt;doesn&amp;#8217;t get spoiled&lt;/a&gt; when application windows are slathered over it. I went with a couple more &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/floater81/4432979527/in/photostream" title="Superb pictures of the second severn crossing"&gt;Burnsy&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/floater81/4432979527/" title="The Second Severn Crossing by mattburns.co.uk, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2723/4432979527_aaac753da6.jpg" width="500" height="333" alt="The Second Severn Crossing"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember the second Severn crossing being built. I&amp;#8217;d just moved to Bristol, joining a company which did virtual reality. The hardware was too expensive and the software too slow but we were a good team. Summer lunchtimes, we would play frisbee on the grassy hill by the Almondsbury garden centre. You could see the estuary, the new concrete pylons stepping into it, and, rising to the East, the towers of the original suspension bridge. Anyone who cycles around Bristol knows this view well. Interval training with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/drbyrne255/status/187257262748876800"&gt;Owen&lt;/a&gt;, we spin out along Passage Road and catch our breath before turning back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="540" height="256" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" src="https://maps.google.co.uk/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=embed&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=aust&amp;amp;aq=&amp;amp;sll=51.587465,-4.195722&amp;amp;sspn=0.019305,0.035963&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hq=&amp;amp;hnear=Aust,+South+Gloucestershire,+United+Kingdom&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;layer=c&amp;amp;cbll=51.593919,-2.632873&amp;amp;panoid=b9ap7_VnelTDzEUhtGFcPQ&amp;amp;cbp=13,259.11,,0,0&amp;amp;ll=51.590016,-2.632856&amp;amp;spn=0.013651,0.046349&amp;amp;z=14&amp;amp;output=svembed"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently I&amp;#8217;ve moved to Swansea but kept my job in Bristol, crossing from and to Wales &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Severn_Tunnel" title="The tunnel was built by the Great Western Railway between 1873 and 1886"&gt;under the river&lt;/a&gt; twice a week, Tuesdays and Thursdays, working from home on Mondays and Fridays. Now that too has come to an end. We were a good team but &amp;#8230; anyway. My new job will be home-based. Next I&amp;#8217;ll be partitioning the hard drive and booting into Linux.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align:center"&gt;&amp;sect;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thanks, again, to &lt;a href="http://www.mattburns.co.uk/mattburns.html"&gt;Matt Burns&lt;/a&gt; for allowing me to use his superb photos.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/desktop-preferences#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; Which reminds me, I should write about a cunning data structure which lazily initialises a sparse vector. &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org" title="Once popular, now dormant programming blog"&gt;Wordaligned.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; a programming blog, honest.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2012-06-21</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/desktop-preferences</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/desktop-preferences</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Think, quote, escape</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Evidently Jamie had got in before me. Somehow he&amp;#8217;d unpacked the new 2U server and balanced it on the side of his desk. He looked hassled. I didn&amp;#8217;t ask. The server&amp;#8217;s fans whirred noisily. On Jamie&amp;#8217;s second monitor I could see the familiar chatter of Linux installing itself. I stepped over the cardboard and polystyrene, sat, woke my machine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments later I heard the install disk eject. Jamie typed something, cursed. The disk clattered into the bin. The room grew quiet as the server shut down.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were a small, new team. Nonetheless, we&amp;#8217;d put something substantial together. It built on a Java framework and ran on Linux. We&amp;#8217;d tweaked the framework, meaning we had to build it from source before building our own stuff, so a clean build took almost half an hour. Just over half an hour later, Jamie had burned a new install disk. He placed it in the server&amp;#8217;s DVD drive. The fans roared up again. Ten minutes later, more cursing, another disk in the bin.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walked across. Jamie was glaring at some code. A Perl list? His cursor was poised over an item in this list, a single-quoted string, inside which was a sed command, whose arguments themselves needed quoting, which was evidently meant to edit the contents of a double-quoted string in some configuration file. Think: quote and escape. I could see there were &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; DVDs in the bin. Jamie must have been in for some time. No wonder he looked hassled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&amp;#8217;s up?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trade show in the States. The salesman was out there. A bare machine had already been delivered and he needed the software, so Jamie had to cut a DVD which would directly install the operating system together with our application. Please don&amp;#8217;t expect a salesman to download an ISO image and set up enough of a network to boot from it. A courier was booked for midday to collect the DVD. That&amp;#8217;s what&amp;#8217;s up. So leave me alone and let me get on with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He didn&amp;#8217;t actually say that last bit. It&amp;#8217;s true, though, he was the Linux expert. I stubbornly watched as he changed some double quotes for single ones, added a couple more backslashes, checked in the file, kicked off another build.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back at my desk, I reviewed the version control change logs. Evidently Jamie was working on a post-install script which took the form of a list of actions which would be evaluated and executed in Perl. Looking at the file diffs, the sticking point seemed to be a sed command to edit the X display settings. Embedding sed within Perl was proving tricky.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jamie&amp;#8217;s edit-build-burn-install-check cycle seemed crazy to me. Why not recreate the broken post-install step as a standalone operation? Soon enough I&amp;#8217;d found a way to reproduce the problem. After reading documentation and experimenting I figured out how to nest and escape the various strings. I admit, it took me longer than I expected. By this time Jamie solved the problem by trial and error anyway &amp;#8212; and as proof he had an install disk which he knew worked. He may well have spent less time actually concentrating on the issue than I had; the build-burn-install phases of his process all ran as background activities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the event we needed to revise the software anyway. So the salesman had to download a new build at the last minute. Jamie stayed late the next day to talk him through the installation.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2010-03-30</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/think-quote-escape</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/think-quote-escape</link>
<category>Self</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
