<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Word Aligned, hosted by Github</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;To anyone who subscribes to this site&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt;, my apologies if your reader recently got filled with items you&amp;#8217;d already seen. I can explain.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About seven years ago, I signed up for a great deal on hosting for life with a company called &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/hosting-for-life-textdrive-revived.html"&gt;TextDrive&lt;/a&gt;. For most of the time since then, this service was actually provided by Joyent &amp;#8212; who took over TextDrive. Then they, Joyent, said the hosting for life deal was being &amp;#8220;sunsetted&amp;#8221;, i.e. canned. Happily TextDrive&amp;#8217;s original founder, Dean Allen, stepped in to revive his company and honour the original offer, which has indeed happened, though it&amp;#8217;s been all too clear that he&amp;#8217;s been hard to get hold of whilst the operations staff have been over-stretched.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, a tweet from one of these hardworking ops tipped me off that TextDrive would soon be gone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public Service Announcement: TextDrivers please note that TextDrive is ceasing operation on the 14th of March 2014  &lt;a href="http://t.co/AMIO3xS2wX"&gt;http://t.co/AMIO3xS2wX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jacques Marneweck (@txdjm) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/txdjm/statuses/441774463386800129"&gt;March 7, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to do?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=static+website+hosting"&gt;googling&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve chosen &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; as the new host for Word Aligned. I&amp;#8217;ve had to relinquish a little control over URLs to make the site truly static. (A side-effect being old content appearing with new identifiers in the RSS &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt;). I also won&amp;#8217;t be configuring a web server or rooting around in rotating log files. The experts at Github can take care of that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do get to keep my own domain, which was paramount. I don&amp;#8217;t have to pay anything, which is nice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, I used version control to track my site&amp;#8217;s contents and &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;SSH&lt;/code&gt; to publish. Now I simply use version control: pushing a change to &lt;a href="https://github.com/wordaligned"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; publication.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s early days yet, but I&amp;#8217;m happy with the change. The &lt;a href="http://feeds.wordaligned.org/wordaligned"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt; should settle down now, so stay subscribed. Please &lt;a href="mailto:tag@wordaligned.org?subject=Wordaligned.org%20glitches"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt; if you spot any problems with the site.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2014-03-13</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/word-aligned-hosted-by-github</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/word-aligned-hosted-by-github</link>
<category>self</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
