<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Unit Tests Questioned</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to &lt;a href="http://swanseasdc.co.uk/events/why-service-oriented-architecture/"&gt;talking at TechHub Swansea&lt;/a&gt; at the end of the month on the subject of unit testing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction to the talk is here. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/"&gt;&lt;img width=640 src="http://wordaligned.org/images/unit-tests-questioned.png" alt="Unit Tests Questioned"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk we&amp;#8217;ll consider if unit testing is a good use of our time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not questioning whether &lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt; is important. This slide shows the abstract of &lt;a href="http://www.gwern.net/docs/1996-hoare.pdf" title="(PDF) How did software get so reliable without proof?"&gt;a paper published in 1996 by Tony Hoare&lt;/a&gt;. What he says is that you don&amp;#8217;t need to &lt;strong&gt;prove&lt;/strong&gt; your software works: you can make it so through design and review; by testing; and by good engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=640 src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/images/how-did-software-get-so-reliable.png" alt="How did software get so reliable without proof?"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may no longer seem controversial or novel but maybe it was a surprising thing for Tony Hoare to say. After all, he invented &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quicksort"&gt;quicksort&lt;/a&gt; back in 1959, an algorithm which he &lt;strong&gt;proved&lt;/strong&gt; correct. He also proved how quickly it runs, and that &amp;#8212; in the general case &amp;#8212; it couldn&amp;#8217;t be beaten. Much of Hoare&amp;#8217;s subsequent research was dedicated to proving software works using techniques known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formal_methods" title="Formal Methods (Wikipedia)"&gt;formal methods&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is that you write a formal specification of what your program should do, and then you mathematically verify your code satisfies that specification. Surely nothing less is good enough for software which really is a matter of life and death: a life support system, or a device driver in a nuclear warhead, for example? Actually, no, he says in this paper, there are more pragmatic routes to reliable software.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the idea that you can build reliability via testing may once have seemed radical. It doesn&amp;#8217;t any more. Maybe, though, the conventional modern wisdom that &lt;strong&gt;unit tests&lt;/strong&gt; are a good thing should be questioned.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/images/coplien.jpg" alt="Coplien" /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James O Coplien voices a dissenting opinion in a more recent paper, &lt;a href="http://rbcs-us.com/documents/Why-Most-Unit-Testing-is-Waste.pdf" title="(PDF) Why Most Unit Testing is Waste"&gt;&amp;#8220;Why most unit testing is waste&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s Cope on about!?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is the force of current thinking that even the title of this paper makes it seem like he&amp;#8217;s trolling. Having read the paper carefully, I don&amp;#8217;t think he is. That doesn&amp;#8217;t mean I agree with him, but I agree with his attitude:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a lot of advice, but very little of it is backed either by theory, data, or even a model of why you should believe a given piece of advice. Good testing begs skepticism. Be skeptical of yourself: measure, prove, retry. Be skeptical of me for heaven&amp;#8217;s sake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, this talk will do just that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unit tests: let&amp;#8217;s get skeptical!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-01-21</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned</link>
<category>self</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
