<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>Meetup? Turn Up!</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Agile-Bath-Bristol/events/245853715/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sell out" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/agile-bb-meetup.png"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monday&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Agile-Bath-Bristol/events/245853715/"&gt;Agile Bath &amp;amp; Bristol meetup&lt;/a&gt; was a sell out. All 50 available spaces were taken. I myself was lucky to get a place &amp;#8212; I was on the waiting list until a spot opened up at 3pm on the day. And I was the speaker!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality turned out to be different: of the 50 who&amp;#8217;d claimed spaces, roughly one in four actually showed up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, it was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue_Monday_(date)"&gt;Blue Monday&lt;/a&gt;. I know, there are bugs going round &amp;#8212; my daughter has been running a fever and didn&amp;#8217;t go in to college, and if I hadn&amp;#8217;t been presenting I myself would have cancelled to stay in with her. I know, your work day over-runs, you&amp;#8217;re hungry, something else comes up. I know, it&amp;#8217;s a free event, so it&amp;#8217;s not as though you&amp;#8217;ve &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; anything.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all these things a 25% turnout reflects badly on us all. It&amp;#8217;s unfair on the sponsors and organisers, especially when refreshments are offered. It&amp;#8217;s impolite to those who turn up at the advertised time, and must then sit waiting in case more people who&amp;#8217;ve said they&amp;#8217;re coming actually show up. It&amp;#8217;s tough on the speakers: planning a session for an audience of 50 is different to one you&amp;#8217;d plan for 12.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise 25% is egregiously low, but &amp;#8212; in my experience &amp;#8212; 50% is far from unusual, and even considered acceptable. I think it&amp;#8217;s shabby. The one excuse noone has is forgetting the event is on &amp;#8212; Meetup etc. integrate with your calendar and issue repeated reminders to attend and requests to cancel if you cannot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my thanks to those who turned up and participated. I enjoyed it. Smaller numbers allowed for a more collaborative session. Ironically, topics discussed included punctuality, respect, commitment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please, don&amp;#8217;t sign up to a meetup you don&amp;#8217;t plan to attend. If you decide to cancel, release your place so someone else can have it. Otherwise, arrive on time.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2018-01-18</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/meetup-turn-up</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/meetup-turn-up</link>
<category>Talks</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>SwanseaCon 2017</title>
<description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Unit tests, lets get sceptical &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/thomasguest"&gt;@thomasguest&lt;/a&gt; was a great end to the morning before lunch &lt;a href="https://t.co/EM4RPAs975"&gt;pic.twitter.com/EM4RPAs975&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; SwanseaCon (@SwanseaCon) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SwanseaCon/status/912361247760404480"&gt;September 25, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m just back from a packed two days at &lt;a href="http://swanseacon.co.uk"&gt;SwanseaCon&lt;/a&gt; and would like to thank the organisers, speakers and participants for making such a welcoming and diverse conference happen right where I live.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, highlights included:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     Professor Dave Snowden&amp;#8217;s erudite and slide-free talk. It was a privilege to listen: although I may not quite have kept up, I will certainly follow up
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Irina Tsyganok&amp;#8217;s sensitive and inspirational presentation on pair-programming
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Lawrence Weetman&amp;#8217;s dishwashing demo &amp;#8212; with three on-stage helpers, no less
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Scott Fulton&amp;#8217;s honest report on some personal agile life lessons
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The venue wasn&amp;#8217;t too shabby either.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/37286571132/in/photostream/" title="The view from SwanseaCon"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4462/37286571132_a5892fe22c_z.jpg" width="640" height="185" alt="The view from SwanseaCon"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src="http://wordaligned.org//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having attended a fair few technical conferences, it felt refreshing and important to be part of something a little softer. Software development is about community, communication and culture, and SwanseaCon scored top marks on all three.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, again, thanks!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-09-26</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/swanseacon-2017</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/swanseacon-2017</link>
<category>Talks</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Unit Tests Questioned</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to &lt;a href="http://swanseasdc.co.uk/events/why-service-oriented-architecture/"&gt;talking at TechHub Swansea&lt;/a&gt; at the end of the month on the subject of unit testing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction to the talk is here. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/"&gt;&lt;img width=640 src="http://wordaligned.org/images/unit-tests-questioned.png" alt="Unit Tests Questioned"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk we&amp;#8217;ll consider if unit testing is a good use of our time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not questioning whether &lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt; is important. This slide shows the abstract of &lt;a href="http://www.gwern.net/docs/1996-hoare.pdf" title="(PDF) How did software get so reliable without proof?"&gt;a paper published in 1996 by Tony Hoare&lt;/a&gt;. What he says is that you don&amp;#8217;t need to &lt;strong&gt;prove&lt;/strong&gt; your software works: you can make it so through design and review; by testing; and by good engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=640 src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/images/how-did-software-get-so-reliable.png" alt="How did software get so reliable without proof?"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may no longer seem controversial or novel but maybe it was a surprising thing for Tony Hoare to say. After all, he invented &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quicksort"&gt;quicksort&lt;/a&gt; back in 1959, an algorithm which he &lt;strong&gt;proved&lt;/strong&gt; correct. He also proved how quickly it runs, and that &amp;#8212; in the general case &amp;#8212; it couldn&amp;#8217;t be beaten. Much of Hoare&amp;#8217;s subsequent research was dedicated to proving software works using techniques known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formal_methods" title="Formal Methods (Wikipedia)"&gt;formal methods&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is that you write a formal specification of what your program should do, and then you mathematically verify your code satisfies that specification. Surely nothing less is good enough for software which really is a matter of life and death: a life support system, or a device driver in a nuclear warhead, for example? Actually, no, he says in this paper, there are more pragmatic routes to reliable software.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the idea that you can build reliability via testing may once have seemed radical. It doesn&amp;#8217;t any more. Maybe, though, the conventional modern wisdom that &lt;strong&gt;unit tests&lt;/strong&gt; are a good thing should be questioned.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/docs/unit-tests/images/coplien.jpg" alt="Coplien" /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James O Coplien voices a dissenting opinion in a more recent paper, &lt;a href="http://rbcs-us.com/documents/Why-Most-Unit-Testing-is-Waste.pdf" title="(PDF) Why Most Unit Testing is Waste"&gt;&amp;#8220;Why most unit testing is waste&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s Cope on about!?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is the force of current thinking that even the title of this paper makes it seem like he&amp;#8217;s trolling. Having read the paper carefully, I don&amp;#8217;t think he is. That doesn&amp;#8217;t mean I agree with him, but I agree with his attitude:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a lot of advice, but very little of it is backed either by theory, data, or even a model of why you should believe a given piece of advice. Good testing begs skepticism. Be skeptical of yourself: measure, prove, retry. Be skeptical of me for heaven&amp;#8217;s sake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, this talk will do just that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unit tests: let&amp;#8217;s get skeptical!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2017-01-21</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/unit-tests-questioned</link>
<category>Talks</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
