<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" >
<channel>
<title>Word Aligned</title>
<link>http://wordaligned.org</link>
<description>tales from the code face</description>
<dc:creator>tag@wordaligned.org</dc:creator>
<language>en-gb</language>
<item>
<title>&#8220;Solutions&#8221;</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I like working around enthusiasts and optimists but that doesn&amp;#8217;t mean I want to use chirpy or bombastic software.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days I build programs using visual studio. Sure, it&amp;#8217;s a decent tool but part of me cringes every time I&amp;#8217;m asked to open a &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;Solution&amp;#8221;&lt;/strong&gt; especially when what I get seems more like a &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;Muddle&amp;#8221;&lt;/strong&gt;. A progress bar slides into action after my program links: &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;Updating Intellisense &amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who coined that galumphing portmanteau? It means auto-completion and I don&amp;#8217;t want to know it&amp;#8217;s going on &amp;#8212; especially since I edit code using &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/accidental-emacs.html"&gt;Emacs&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perforce is new to me and I lean on a &lt;a href="http://www.perforce.com/product/components/perforce-visual-client" title="P4V"&gt;graphical client&lt;/a&gt; so heavily I sometimes trip over it. So when I&amp;#8217;m trying to dance round client workspaces and their half-baked integration with microsoft &lt;del&gt;muddles&lt;/del&gt; solutions, the last thing I want is to be asked to &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;Choose a Favorite Connection&amp;#8221;&lt;/strong&gt;. When it comes to Perforce Servers I don&amp;#8217;t have favourites let alone favorites. Sorry.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2013-04-17</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/solutions</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/solutions</link>
<category>Windows</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Beware the March of IDEs!</title>
<description>&lt;h3&gt;The March of IDEs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio can be one of the programmer&amp;#8217;s best friends, but over the years it has become increasingly pushy, domineering, and suffering from unsettling control issues. Should we just surrender to Visual Studio&amp;#8217;s insistence on writing our code for us? Or is Visual Studio sapping our programming intelligence rather than augmenting it? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212; Charles Petzold, &lt;a href="http://www.charlespetzold.com/etc/DoesVisualStudioRotTheMind.html"&gt;Does Visual Studio Rot the Mind?&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.charlespetzold.com" title="Charles Petzold"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.charlespetzold.com/PetzoldBW.gif" alt="Charles Petzold, Wikipedia"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;a href="http://www.charlespetzold.com/pw5/" title="Programming Windows home page"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.charlespetzold.com/pw5/pw5.png" alt="Programming Windows front cover"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ides_of_March" title="The Ides of March is the name of March 15 in the Roman calendar"&gt;March the 15th&lt;/a&gt; is a good day to revisit a talk &lt;a href="http://www.charlespetzold.com/"&gt;Charles Petzold&lt;/a&gt; gave to at the NYC .NET Developer&amp;#8217;s Group some four and half years ago. The speaker is probably best known as the author of &lt;a href="http://www.charlespetzold.com/pw5/"&gt;Programming Windows&lt;/a&gt;, now in its fifth edition, and during his talk he confesses to a love/hate relationship with the software most people use for Windows programming &amp;#8212; Microsoft Visual Studio (VS).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;#8217;t read the &lt;a href="http://www.charlespetzold.com/etc/DoesVisualStudioRotTheMind.html"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;, read it now; and if you have, give it another look. Charles Petzold frets about the addictive nature of VS: if you become hooked on intellisense will you become dependent and mentally flabby? And what about the code VS generates in directories which it chooses? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beware! Your IDE is taking over: you&amp;#8217;ll end up working for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story has a happy ending. Charles Petzold finds an antidote, working on programs to solve a series of maths puzzles set by &lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/" title="New Scientist web site"&gt;New Scientist&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided to use plain old ANSI C, and to edit the source code in Notepad &amp;#8212; which has no IntelliSense and no sense of any other kind &amp;#8212; and to compile on the command line using both the Microsoft C compiler and the Gnu C compiler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Me and my IDE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rarely use Visual Studio these days, mainly because I&amp;#8217;m primarily developing on Unix platforms. I have used VS in the past, though: but I still turned to Emacs to edit files. For debugging, I&amp;#8217;ll admit VS is peerless. VS project files aren&amp;#8217;t portable. It took someone far more expert than me a considerable amount of time to create a cross-platform build system capable of keeping everyone happy. Similarly, a few years ago I spent a short while doing Java development on Linux. Again, I tended to fall back on Emacs for editing, while using &lt;a href="http://www.eclipse.org/"&gt;Eclipse&lt;/a&gt; to enforce style rules, tidy imports, debug, that kind of thing. I would have used Eclipse more but it kept on crashing. When I first started developing on a Mac I tried out XCode. It opened far too many windows and GDB didn&amp;#8217;t seem to want to play with it. I abandoned it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/accidental-emacs.html" title="Things I discovered about Emacs, by accident"&gt;I do use Emacs&lt;/a&gt; as an IDE for code development, and for everything else, but it&amp;#8217;s set up the way I want and it never tries to smooth over the details of what it&amp;#8217;s up to. I frequently drop into the shell (even if it&amp;#8217;s a shell running within Emacs).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest problem with the traditional IDE is the view it imposes on a software project. The IDE makes you feel like you&amp;#8217;re an airplane pilot sitting in front of a bank of controls, steering great swathes of code on a demanding course. The &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;DE emphasises integration; it&amp;#8217;s in danger of creating &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;nterdependencies, of coupling everything. I prefer something more focused.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Learning to Say &amp;#8220;Hello, World&amp;#8221;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596809492"&gt;&lt;img src="http://covers.oreilly.com/images/9780596809492/cat.gif" alt="97TEPSK cover"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a while to reach this view. Charles Petzold&amp;#8217;s epiphany is almost identical to one I had myself, many years ago. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of last year, O&amp;#8217;Reilly books posed the question: What 97 things should every programmer programmer know? In answer, I wrote about the moment I decided to shut down my IDE and get back to basics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the story, &lt;a href="http://programmer.97things.oreilly.com/wiki/index.php/Learn_to_Say_%22Hello,_World%22" title="My contribution to 97 Things Every Programmer Should Know"&gt;Learn to Say &amp;#8220;Hello, World&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; on the wiki which was used for developing the book. Alternatively, the submission was accepted for publication, so you can buy &lt;a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596809492"&gt;the book&lt;/a&gt; itself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The Ides of March&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/cm/s/silver_denarius_of_marcus_juni.aspx" alt="A coin celebrating ancient Rome's most famous murder"/&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.britishmuseum.org/images/an107083_m.jpg" alt="A coin celebrating ancient Rome's most famous murder"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This [silver denarius] was struck in honour of Marcus Junius Brutus, one of the assassins of Julius Caesar. The reverse shows the cap of liberty given to freed slaves flanked by two daggers. This indicates Brutus&amp;#8217; intention of freeing Rome from Caesar&amp;#8217;s imperial ambitions and the murder weapons employed to do so. Below is the day of the deed; EID.MAR, the ides of March.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212; From the &lt;a href="http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/cm/s/silver_denarius_of_marcus_juni.aspx" title="A coin celebrating ancient Rome's most famous murder"&gt;British Museum&lt;/a&gt; collection
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thanks to &lt;a href="http://curbralan.com/" title="Curbralan, Kevlin Henney's consultancy"&gt;Kevlin Henney&lt;/a&gt; for editing my contribution to &lt;a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596809492"&gt;97 Things Every Programmer Should Know&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed to everyone at O&amp;#8217;Reilly involved with putting the book together.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could claim the title of this blog post was my own invention. I&amp;#8217;m also struggling to remember where I first heard it. I think it might have been Matt Bowers, who also invented &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/antisocial-build-orders.html" title="Anti-Social Build Orders"&gt;build ASBOs&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone?
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2010-03-15</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/beware-the-march-of-ides</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/beware-the-march-of-ides</link>
<category>Windows</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Tell me about &#8230; Virtualization</title>
<description>&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocintroduction" name="toc0" id="toc0"&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocvirtualization-in-general" name="toc1" id="toc1"&gt;Virtualization in general&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toccreating-a-virtual-machine" name="toc2" id="toc2"&gt;Creating a virtual machine&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocheres-one-we-made-earlier" name="toc3" id="toc3"&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s one we made earlier&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocrunning-a-virtual-machine" name="toc4" id="toc4"&gt;Running a virtual machine&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocperipheral-access" name="toc5" id="toc5"&gt;Peripheral Access&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocopportunities" name="toc6" id="toc6"&gt;Opportunities&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocconsiderations" name="toc7" id="toc7"&gt;Considerations&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocjust-for-fun" name="toc8" id="toc8"&gt;Just for fun&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocfurther-reading" name="toc9" id="toc9"&gt;Further reading&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#tocthanks" name="toc10" id="toc10"&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc0" name="tocintroduction" id="tocintroduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization solves a computing problem by adding a layer of indirection. The problem being: how to run multiple operating systems on a single computer; and the indirection: to slip a software shim between a guest operating system and the hosting platform, which continues to run its native operating system.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/imac-parallels.png" alt="Imac running OS X, Windows XP, Linux"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example makes this clear. I work on an Apple computer which runs OS X, a flavour of BSD Unix. To develop portable code which will build and run on Linux and Windows as well as OS X, I use virtualization software. Using this software enables my Apple computer to run (for example) Windows XP and Linux Fedora Core 7 as guest operating systems alongside its native OS X. Effectively, I have three computers running on the same physical machine with no need for extra power supplies, keyboards, mice, monitors and so on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/vmware.gif" style="float:right" alt="VMware logo"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com/"&gt;Parallels Desktop&lt;/a&gt; virtualization software I use doesn&amp;#8217;t come free but it&amp;#8217;s cheaper and more convenient than buying more hardware. &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com"&gt;VMware&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps the single biggest name in virtualization, does offer free entry-level products for doing a similar job on Windows and Linux platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/parallels-logo.gif" style="float:right" alt="Parallels logo"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article will not provide details on installing and configuring virtualization software, troubleshooting problems, and so on: the products have matured to the extent that these details are hardly needed, and any problems are quickly answered by online forums. We won&amp;#8217;t attempt to explain how exactly virtualization works. Instead, we&amp;#8217;ll talk more about what virtualization is, how we can use it, and why we should be interested it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc1" name="tocvirtualization-in-general" id="tocvirtualization-in-general"&gt;Virtualization in general&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we go further I should explain this article uses the term &amp;#8220;virtualization&amp;#8221; in the specific way described in the introduction. More generally, in computing, virtualization refers to the abstraction in software of the platform on which a program runs. The Java Virtual Machine is a well known example, allowing software developers to build a single executable which should run on any machine. The JVM also isolates the application from the rest of the machine. These advantages, of portability and isolation, also apply to the full  virtualization we&amp;#8217;ll discuss in this article.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc2" name="toccreating-a-virtual-machine" id="toccreating-a-virtual-machine"&gt;Creating a virtual machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a virtual machine feels just like setting up a normal machine, except you don&amp;#8217;t need new hardware. All you need is your host machine, the guest operating system media, and a suitable license to use it. With your host up and running, mount the install media, start up the virtualization software, click &amp;#8220;Create new machine&amp;#8221;, and follow the prompts. You&amp;#8217;ll have to specify what resources to grant the machine (disk space, RAM, etc.) but very quickly you&amp;#8217;ll be following the standard install procedure for your guest OS, selecting languages, packages and so on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#8217;t need actual physical media: you can create your virtual machine by booting it up from a DVD image on disk or over a network in much the same way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc3" name="tocheres-one-we-made-earlier" id="tocheres-one-we-made-earlier"&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s one we made earlier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, you may not require &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; install media. Your virtualization software is capable of booting up a pre-built virtual machine. VMware terms such machines &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com/appliances/"&gt;virtual appliances&lt;/a&gt;. Running such an appliance is as easy as downloading it (which, at around 300Mb or less, requires far less bandwidth than a typical install image) and clicking on the downloaded file.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you&amp;#8217;ll typically be getting is a stripped-down Unix server, pre-built for a specific purpose, with stable, tested, compatible versions of whatever packages it requires for that purpose, and capable of operating within, say, 256Mb of RAM and as much hard disk as you&amp;#8217;re prepared to allow it. You can run this Unix server on a Windows machine. You can reconfigure it. You can even transfer it to a different machine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, suppose you want evaluate &lt;a href="http://trac.edgewall.org"&gt;Trac&lt;/a&gt;, an integrated version control and project management application. Trac may be open-source, popular and free, but I can personally vouch that on a Unix system it takes some setting up, and I can&amp;#8217;t imagine getting it to work natively on a Windows server. Using virtualization, you simply download a virtual machine which has been loaded with the latest stable release of Trac. Boot up this machine using your host virtualisation software and run it on any supported operating system &amp;#8212; Windows included. Do the same with &lt;a href="http://www.redmine.org"&gt;Redmine&lt;/a&gt;, another web-based project management application, and you can compare it with Trac. Once you&amp;#8217;ve completed your evaluation, delete the one you don&amp;#8217;t like and keep going with the other. As a virtual machine, it&amp;#8217;s easy to move it to a new host, if desired. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.jumpbox.com"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://www.jumpbox.com/sites/all/themes/jumpbox/logo-white.gif" alt="JumpBox logo"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VMware provide instructions for creating appliances and host a &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com/appliances/"&gt;library of such appliances&lt;/a&gt; on their website. Organisations like &lt;a href="http://www.jumpbox.com"&gt;JumpBox&lt;/a&gt; make a business out of providing virtual machines which run on a number of different virtual platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc4" name="tocrunning-a-virtual-machine" id="tocrunning-a-virtual-machine"&gt;Running a virtual machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img style="float:right" src="http://wordaligned.org/images/win-xp-and-fc7.gif" alt="Virtual machine shortcuts"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parallels Desktop creates shortcuts which I click on to power up the virtual machines. VMware on Windows does something similar. My perception is that these virtual machines boot as quickly as their physical counterparts would, but it could simply be that I&amp;#8217;m using the host system to do something else while they  start up in the background.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly how the guest operating system integrates with the host varies. Some systems/configurations give you a window within a window; the guest user interface is displayed as a whole within a single window on the host, and you switch focus to this window to use it. More sophisticated systems integrate seamlessly, so you can tab between host and guest applications as if they were all running natively, and guest and host file browsers see both machines&amp;#8217; file systems transparently. The end-user experience is of the host and guest operating in parallel, as a single computer which can run software native to both systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the first mode can be awkward to use. I much prefer the second: any friction context-switching between machines, and you find yourself preferring separate machines and a KVM, or using an X server to display X windows presented by a remote machine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc5" name="tocperipheral-access" id="tocperipheral-access"&gt;Peripheral Access&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which peripherals can the guest operating system access? Certainly, the guest wouldn&amp;#8217;t be much use if it couldn&amp;#8217;t make use of monitor, keyboard and mouse &amp;#8212; although you may suffer translation and configuration wrinkles due to the different keyboard layout and mouse button conventions used by different operating systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to other peripherals and interfaces will depend on the virtualization software: check the product information. My guest Windows XP can use its host&amp;#8217;s:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     network interfaces
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     USB ports
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     DVD drive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     speakers
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     built-in camera
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, I didn&amp;#8217;t realise it could use the camera, having never had cause to use the camera from within Windows, but a quick check shows it can. Access to networked printers also just works.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc6" name="tocopportunities" id="tocopportunities"&gt;Opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve already mentioned some obvious uses for virtualization, and I&amp;#8217;ll add some more which I&amp;#8217;ve found useful in the past:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     you can develop for multiple platforms using a single machine
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     you can download pre-built machines designed to run particular applications, saving you from package management headaches
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     if you use a laptop, virtualization allows you to carry many machines around with you: a sales person could demonstrate Unix-based software on a Windows machine, for example
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     you can script the creation of machines, and test e.g. clustered server configurations, without needing a rack filled with hardware
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     you can test on multiple platforms
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if your application itself is server-based and only runs on a single platform, virtualization allows you to test its web interface on multiple browsers. And even if your development is tied to a single operating system, virtualization allows you to keep old versions of that operating system alive on new hardware, and indeed to constrain the resources available to these old versions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hosting companies often use virtualization to create an indirection between user accounts and the hosting hardware farm. Users have root access to their own virtual machine yet are isolated from other root users on the same hardware (for example, rebooting a virtual machine doesn&amp;#8217;t affect other machines on the same host); and their virtual machine can be transferred between physical hosts without them even realising.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would even be possible to distribute software as a virtual appliance. Rather than requiring your users to install version X of Python, version Y of SQLite, version Z of the database bindings and so on, you might consider distributing an entire system which runs as a virtual machine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc7" name="tocconsiderations" id="tocconsiderations"&gt;Considerations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running a virtual machine requires real resources. I deliberately chose Windows XP over Vista for this reason; XP has the smaller footprint and it&amp;#8217;s all I personally need for developing software which ports to Windows.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already mentioned, your guest operating system needs licensing. You need to pay to use Windows even if you&amp;#8217;re running it on an Apple computer and have already paid for OS X. You&amp;#8217;ll also need to go through the usual activation procedure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll need to tend to your virtual machines like any others on your local network. They need naming and backing up. User accounts must be created. Depending on what presence they have on your network, you may want to configure DHCP, or take anti-virus measures. You also need to consider upgrading them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have run into wrinkles and irritations with the hardware abstraction side of virtualization. For example, the Apple keyboard I use doesn&amp;#8217;t map exactly to what I&amp;#8217;d want when using Windows. It&amp;#8217;s occasionally taken me some fiddling with X configuration files to get a Linux graphical interface displaying properly. Generally, though, someone else will have found and fixed the problem before you, and searching online forums turns up an answer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article&amp;#8217;s introduction we classed virtualization as yet another computing problem solved by indirection. Indirection has a price. What about the accumulated expense of everything passing through the software shim which abstracts the platform? Surely a guest operating system can&amp;#8217;t be as fast as a native one on equivalent hardware? I have no hard figures to present here but personal experience suggests no perceptible difference: the only thing I have noticed is that my guest Windows XP seems to use only one of its host&amp;#8217;s two CPUs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc8" name="tocjust-for-fun" id="tocjust-for-fun"&gt;Just for fun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve seen it&amp;#8217;s possible and sensible for a platform to host a guest operating system within its native operating system. How about trying something silly? Could our guest operating system itself use virtualization to become a host for a guest of its own?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave it a go. Using Parallels Desktop on my OS X host, running Windows XP as a guest, I installed (the free) VMware Player virtualization software for Windows. So far, so good. Next I downloaded vmTrac, a 113Mb VMware appliance which packages Trac, Subversion, WebMin and Lighttpd on a FreeBSD core. I extracted the archive and opened the appliance using VMware Player. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture shows my desktop. I&amp;#8217;ve used Google Chrome and Internet Explorer to access Trac and WebMin, which are running as web applications on FreeBSD, itself running as a Windows XP guest, and Windows XP is a guest on OS X.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2851613748/" title="Virtualization by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3011/2851613748_0d3db38a4a.jpg" width="500" height="313" alt="virtualization" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc9" name="tocfurther-reading" id="tocfurther-reading"&gt;Further reading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although virtualization products are mature and modern hardware is ready to accommodate them, the options and possibilities still take some explaining. You&amp;#8217;ll find plenty of good material on the &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com"&gt;VMware&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com/"&gt;Parallels&lt;/a&gt; websites. It&amp;#8217;s also worth searching for other virtualization platforms. This is a growing market, there are lots of competitors and good deals to be had.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.justsoftwaresolutions.co.uk/testing/testing-on-multiple-platforms-with-vmware.html"&gt;Testing on Multiple Platforms with VMware&lt;/a&gt;, by Anthony Williams provides a clear overview of the subject addressed in this article.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization#toc10" name="tocthanks" id="tocthanks"&gt;Thanks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/aboutus/aboutjournals"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://accu.org/content/images/journals/CVu205Cover.png" alt="CVu 20.5 cover"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was first published in CVu 20.5, an &lt;a href="http://accu.org/index.php/aboutus/aboutjournals"&gt;ACCU journal&lt;/a&gt;, and I would like to thank everyone at CVu for their help with it. In particular, I&amp;#8217;d like to thank Gail Ollis, who edited CVu 20.5, and who suggested contributors should try and step back from the details of &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; to do something, and instead explain &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; exactly that something is and &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; it might be of interest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This remit inspired several authors and CVu 20.5 turned out to be a great read. I particularly enjoyed Matthew Wilson&amp;#8217;s article, &amp;#8220;!(C ^ C++)&amp;#8221;. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Wilson_(author)"&gt;Matthew Wilson&lt;/a&gt; is known as a C++ expert, but it came as no surprise to find he also knows his way around C. What did surprise me was to discover he prefers to use C in certain situations, and why.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2009-01-07</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/virtualization</link>
<category>Windows</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Your computer might be at risk</title>
<description>&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tochard-drive-failure" name="toc0" id="toc0"&gt;Hard drive failure&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocrecovery-strategy" name="toc1" id="toc1"&gt;Recovery strategy&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocfree-file-recovery-software" name="toc2" id="toc2"&gt;&amp;#8220;Free&amp;#8221; file recovery software&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocrestoring-the-machine" name="toc3" id="toc3"&gt;Restoring the machine&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocnetgear-wireless-pci-card" name="toc4" id="toc4"&gt;Netgear Wireless PCI card&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocflash-install-problems" name="toc5" id="toc5"&gt;Flash install problems&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocthe-antivirus-racket" name="toc6" id="toc6"&gt;The antivirus racket&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocyou-idiot" name="toc7" id="toc7"&gt;You idiot!&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocalternatives" name="toc8" id="toc8"&gt;Alternatives&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocthe-future-of-operating-systems" name="toc9" id="toc9"&gt;The future of operating systems&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#tocback-in-the-present" name="toc10" id="toc10"&gt;Back in the present&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I dislike all three major OS &amp;#8212; Windows, Mac, Linux.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212; &lt;a href="http://www.stifflog.com/2006/10/16/stiff-asks-great-programmers-answer/"&gt;Peter Norvig, Stifflog interview&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although I write software for a living and write about writing software in my spare time, I don&amp;#8217;t like computers much. I&amp;#8217;m not afraid of them. I&amp;#8217;m not completely incompetent at operating them. They just don&amp;#8217;t behave the way I&amp;#8217;d like. Here&amp;#8217;s an example.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc0" name="tochard-drive-failure" id="tochard-drive-failure"&gt;Hard drive failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family computer wouldn&amp;#8217;t boot. Instead it came up with white text on a blue screen listing register contents in hex. A hardware check confirmed my fears: &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=error+code+7"&gt;Error Code 7&lt;/a&gt;, hard drive failure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was irritating but not so very surprising: it&amp;#8217;s an aging computer which had been running Windows XP progressively more and more slowly, and which was almost exclusively used by the kids for playing games on. On more than one occasion it had frozen and needed a hard reboot. What&amp;#8217;s more saddening but also not so very surprising is that our domestic backup policy isn&amp;#8217;t as good as it should be. There were some files on the dead drive we wanted to recover.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even though Gail and I each have our own laptops, it soon became apparent how important a part of family life the defunct desktop was. Our children enjoy playing computer games. They like to watch &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/merlin/"&gt;Merlin on iPlayer&lt;/a&gt;. We needed their machine back.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately I had a laptop and internet access. After hunting through shelves and drawers I reckoned I could get my hands on most of the original install media. It didn&amp;#8217;t take long to come up with a recovery strategy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc1" name="tocrecovery-strategy" id="tocrecovery-strategy"&gt;Recovery strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.getdigital.de/products/Any_Key"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://www.getdigital.de/images/produkte/t2/t2_anykey.jpg" alt="Any Key"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan was:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     disconnect the dead drive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     connect a new drive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     install Windows on the new drive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     reconnect the dead drive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     boot Windows from the new drive
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     try and recover files from the dead drive
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; meant to be a tutorial on recovering from hard drive failures &amp;#8212; if that&amp;#8217;s what you&amp;#8217;re after, the sanest source of information I found was this &lt;a href="http://forums.techarena.in/windows-xp-support/730578.htm#post2775674"&gt;forum post by Patrick Keenan&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; but I do want to stress here that when you get to stage 5 you should &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; allow windows to run a disk check on the dead drive, which is what it defaults to doing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be ready to skip the check by pressing the Any Key!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc2" name="tocfree-file-recovery-software" id="tocfree-file-recovery-software"&gt;&amp;#8220;Free&amp;#8221; file recovery software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first few stages of this plan were tedious but straightforward. I nursed the machine through the Windows XP installation onto a new drive. Since the desktop was designed to accommodate a second hard drive, slotting in the dead drive alongside the new one was idiot-proof. One minor wrinkle: the system didn&amp;#8217;t automatically register the new drive. I had to press F12 to interrupt the boot sequence, enter the BIOS and explicitly enable the drive. By now, I felt quite comfortable with the BIOS screens: this stuff works!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On reboot I skipped the default disk check, as mentioned. My hope was that the physical memory on the dead drive could still be read and that some lower level file reader utility could patch together enough of the file-system for me to recover what I needed. By the way, at this point the PC had no network access. Evidently Windows XP hadn&amp;#8217;t installed a driver for the wireless PCI card. Fortunately the USB ports were functional, so I could download software on the laptop and transfer it to the desktop.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;#8217;t prepared to pay for any file recovery software (yet). The value of the lost files wasn&amp;#8217;t that high, especially if I couldn&amp;#8217;t get them back. Surely I could &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=free+hard+drive+recovery+software"&gt;find some freeware&lt;/a&gt;? I took a couple of wrong turnings here and ended up feeling rather gullible. The top few search hits led me to software I could download and demo for free, which claimed they could do the job, but which I&amp;#8217;d have to pay to use.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.diskinternals.com/products/ntfs-reader/"&gt;DiskInternals NTFS Reader&lt;/a&gt; turned out to be what I was looking for. I&amp;#8217;m sure there are others. Happily I&amp;#8217;d soon managed to locate and recover the files we wanted, and could disconnect the faulty drive. Phew!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc3" name="tocrestoring-the-machine" id="tocrestoring-the-machine"&gt;Restoring the machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restoring the files was one thing. Next I needed to restore the machine itself to full functionality. The screen resolution wasn&amp;#8217;t right. Screen repaints were jaggy. It couldn&amp;#8217;t access the internet. There was no sound (apart from an annoying system beep). Etc. etc. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s going on here? I&amp;#8217;m running a licensed copy of the world&amp;#8217;s most popular operating system on hardware purchased from the world&amp;#8217;s best known PC dealer, not some bleeding edge Linux distribution. Surely it should just work!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hobbyists may delight in tinkering and fixing computers. Not me. I&amp;#8217;m not  clueless, though, and I did realise that what I needed to do was keep downloading and installing drivers until everything behaved. It would have been nice if the system had been a little more self aware, though. Why couldn&amp;#8217;t it tell me why it wasn&amp;#8217;t working? Why couldn&amp;#8217;t it at least provide a hardware manifest in some standard format?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#8217;t bore you with the details of what followed. You don&amp;#8217;t need me to tell you about the repeated reboots, broken download links, quirky installers; like me, you&amp;#8217;ll be immune to the screenfuls of THREATENING LEGAL MUMBO JUMBO YOU HAVE TO AGREE TO. But I do want to highlight a couple of egregious examples of what I&amp;#8217;m talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc4" name="tocnetgear-wireless-pci-card" id="tocnetgear-wireless-pci-card"&gt;Netgear Wireless PCI card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the original install media for the wireless PCI card, and this got the machine connected to the internet. I didn&amp;#8217;t just have to reboot to complete the installation, though, I also needed to physically remove the card and reseat it halfway through the process. Good job the PC chassis was already open. As if all this wasn&amp;#8217;t bad enough, I also had to bypass a grim warning from Windows XP about destabilizing my system. Lovely!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/install-netgear-warning.png" alt="Netgear WG311 install warnings"/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2807550653/" title="alex-rant by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3112/2807550653_43ac2d3d2f_m.jpg" width="202" height="240" alt="alex-rant" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I discovered wireless internet access only worked for system administrators, a level of privilege no one should really need to run at. &lt;a href="http://www.velocityreviews.com/forums/t4522-no-limited-account-connectivity-netgear-wg311twg624t.html"&gt;Googling the problem&lt;/a&gt; suggested I was not alone. So I downloaded the latest drivers, uninstalled the original version, reinstalled the new (power off, remove the old card, power on, install software, power off, insert card, power on, finish installing the software) only to find the driver problems still had not been fixed!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work around the problem I had to follow the install procedure for a third time, in this case &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; clicking through the recommended path, but rather allowing the Windows network connection manager to run the wireless service. Even then I had to stop the Netgear software from auto-starting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grrrr!!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc5" name="tocflash-install-problems" id="tocflash-install-problems"&gt;Flash install problems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids like playing Adobe Flash games so I installed the Flash browser plugin. Well, I tried. Apparently I&amp;#8217;d run out of disk space.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bugs.adobe.com/jira/browse/FP-907"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/install-flash-bug.png" alt="Install Flash bug"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alarming message, considering H:\WINDOWS\system32 was a directory on my brand new, unpartitioned and almost empty 500 GB hard drive! A little more googling revealed that &lt;a href="http://bugs.adobe.com/jira/browse/FP-907"&gt;the Flash installer actually required the presence of a C: drive&lt;/a&gt;. After mounting a USB flash drive and fiddling about with the control panel to remap drive labels, I managed to get Flash plugged in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfunnily enough, I recently faced a similar but less tractable issue at work, trying to get the Flash plugin working on a Red Hat Linux box. Why should running Flash require me to upgrade libc!?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc6" name="tocthe-antivirus-racket" id="tocthe-antivirus-racket"&gt;The antivirus racket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checklist:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
     Hardware happy? &amp;#x2713;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Software happy? &amp;#x2713;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;
     Computer happy? &amp;#x2718;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the clean install of properly licensed software on a new hard drive, &lt;strong&gt;Your computer might be at risk&lt;/strong&gt;. Clicking the balloon to fix the problem directs me to the Microsoft antivirus partners page, where plenty of companies will be happy to help &amp;#8212; at a price, that is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/antivirus-balloon.png" alt="Antivirus Balloon"/&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/3027199004/" title="antivirus-partners by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3283/3027199004_581f3bf8d6_m.jpg" width="240" height="158" alt="antivirus-partners" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, I think, is the final straw. I&amp;#8217;m no longer willing to play along with this racket. The antivirus software &lt;strong&gt;is itself a virus&lt;/strong&gt;, a virus carried by my reconstructed computer from the moment I installed Windows; and clicking the threatening balloon will only make things worse. In the computer&amp;#8217;s former life, I installed some free antivirus software which turned out to be &lt;span /&gt;free as in free beer, not free as in without cost. It soaked up resources, hammered the hard drive mercilessly, and was forever interrupting me, cajoling and wheedling me to upgrade to the professional edition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc7" name="tocyou-idiot" id="tocyou-idiot"&gt;You idiot!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a software professional I should know better. I should know better than run Windows. I should know about security. I should know about backups. I had a lucky escape, and I&amp;#8217;ll admit, I was lazy, but the truth is this kind of thing happens to computer users &amp;#8212; both professional and amateur &amp;#8212; all the time, and many have been burned far worse than me. I think the model of standalone computers with their own hard drives running their own operating system is all wrong, and bolting on an external hard-drive and some backup software doesn&amp;#8217;t make it all right.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc8" name="tocalternatives" id="tocalternatives"&gt;Alternatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;#8217;m not inspired to go out and buy another computer plus the additional hardware and software required to make the house a secure and safe place for computing. It&amp;#8217;s a home, not a server farm!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, if we went the Apple route and purchased hardware and software in beautiful (but expensive!) self-contained packages the driver problems ought to disappear and &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/features/timemachine.html"&gt;time machine&lt;/a&gt; would allow me to chase backwards and recover anything and everything. I&amp;#8217;ll admit I&amp;#8217;m tempted, but I have my concerns about vendor lock-in: if being tied to a software application is bad, being tied to a platform is worse. And yes, if we went the Ubuntu route I don&amp;#8217;t think we&amp;#8217;d be troubled by the antivirus protection racket but I suspect I&amp;#8217;d still end up grubbing round for drivers, possibly with even less success, and I&amp;#8217;m sure it wouldn&amp;#8217;t be such a good games platform.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://norvig.com" title="Peter Norvig's homepage"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" alt="Picture of Peter Norvig" src="http://pn.smugmug.com/photos/343788298_VRnZs-S.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an &lt;a href="http://www.stifflog.com/2006/10/16/stiff-asks-great-programmers-answer/"&gt;interview on stifflog&lt;/a&gt; a number of well known programmers answer questions about their favourite tools (operating systems, languages, editors etc.) I sympathise with Peter Norvig&amp;#8217;s rather negative answer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;I dislike all three major OS &amp;#8212; Windows, Mac, Linux. I like Python and Lisp. Emacs.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer the model of computing as a service, a service you connect to from a variety of devices in a variety of locations. I don&amp;#8217;t really care where exactly my data is &amp;#8212; I just want (secure) access to it, wherever, whenever. I don&amp;#8217;t want a house full of wires and hard drives. Backup should be transparent to me as a user, and it should be straightforward for service providers to implement: bytes are easy to replicate and transmit, to distribute, and there are economies of scale. (For what it&amp;#8217;s worth, my personal backup strategy, based around &lt;a href="http://diveintomark.org/archives/2008/11/03/the-pursuit-of-happiness"&gt;travelling light&lt;/a&gt;, internet access, version control, cron and rysnc, does what it can to emulate this model, but it certainly isn&amp;#8217;t for everyone.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think this a Utopian view and I certainly don&amp;#8217;t claim it&amp;#8217;s original: computing has been gradually moving in this direction for some time now. Perhaps, though, we should refuse to accept the dystopia we&amp;#8217;re currently living with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc9" name="tocthe-future-of-operating-systems" id="tocthe-future-of-operating-systems"&gt;The future of operating systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll have to look hard for an honest and open insider&amp;#8217;s assessment of the state of Mac and Windows, but the Unix community have always been quick to acknowledge design limitations. In an &lt;a href="http://interviews.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=04/10/18/1153211&amp;amp;tid=189&amp;amp;tid=156&amp;amp;tid=130&amp;amp;tid=11"&gt;interview on Slashdot, Rob Pike explains&lt;/a&gt; how weak the Unix design has become in the networked world we live in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The major things we saw wrong with Unix [&amp;#8230;] back around 1985, all stemmed from the appearance of a network. As a stand-alone system, Unix was pretty good. But when you networked Unix machines together, you got a network of stand-alone systems instead of a seamless, integrated networked system. Instead of one big file system, one user community, one secure setup uniting your network of machines, you had a hodgepodge of workarounds to Unix&amp;#8217;s fundamental design decision that each machine is self-sufficient.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We really are using a 1970s era operating system well past its sell-by date. We get a lot done, and we have fun, but let&amp;#8217;s face it, the fundamental design of Unix is older than many of the readers of Slashdot, while lots of different, great ideas about computing and networks have been developed in the last 30 years. Using Unix is the computing equivalent of listening only to music by David Cassidy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the same interview, Rob Pike clears up a misconception. Although he co-authored a book on about Unix, he cannot take credit for its creation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie created Unix and deserve all the credit, and more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which leads us from Slashdot to Google, the computing equivalent of listening to, say, the &lt;a href="http://www.whitestripes.com"&gt;White Stripes&lt;/a&gt;. On the &lt;a href="http://moderator.appspot.com/#15/e=c9&amp;amp;t=2d&amp;amp;q=8e64&amp;amp;v=4"&gt;Ask a Google engineer&lt;/a&gt; forum, Jeff B from Woodstock GA asks a leading question.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I believe the future of operating systems is a &amp;#8220;Cloud OS.&amp;#8221; Do you agree?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Thompson"&gt;Ken Thompson&lt;/a&gt; from Mountain View CA responds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;yes
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk#toc10" name="tocback-in-the-present" id="tocback-in-the-present"&gt;Back in the present&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gifford.co.uk/~coredump/oldsad.htm"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://www.gifford.co.uk/~coredump/zx81_1.jpg" alt="Old sad ZX81"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the remade computer is actually tolerable to use at present. It boots in seconds, has decent peripherals, and (at last!) carries no &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crapware"&gt;craplets&lt;/a&gt;. Having spent a few hours getting to know it, from BIOS, through driver, to control panel, I&amp;#8217;m on better terms with it than ever before. Maybe it&amp;#8217;s not such an &lt;a href="http://www.gifford.co.uk/~coredump/oldsad.htm"&gt;old sad thing&lt;/a&gt; after all.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2008-11-17</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/your-computer-might-be-at-risk</link>
<category>Windows</category>
</item>

<item>
<title>Life, user manuals, recursive pictures</title>
<description>&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocreading-what-to-read" name="toc0" id="toc0"&gt;Reading what to read&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocrecursive-product-packaging" name="toc1" id="toc1"&gt;Recursive product packaging&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocfractals" name="toc2" id="toc2"&gt;Fractals&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocfractals-in-nature" name="toc3" id="toc3"&gt;Fractals in nature&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocwindows-in-windows" name="toc4" id="toc4"&gt;Windows in windows&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocrecursive-paintings-and-prints" name="toc5" id="toc5"&gt;Recursive paintings and prints&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;

 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#tocvalenes-masterpiece" name="toc6" id="toc6"&gt;Valene&amp;#8217;s masterpiece&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc0" name="tocreading-what-to-read" id="tocreading-what-to-read"&gt;Reading what to read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, scouring &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/programming"&gt;proggit&lt;/a&gt; for something worth reading, I found myself &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6rc96/list_of_nontechnical_books_recommended_by_knuth/"&gt;directed&lt;/a&gt; to Don Knuth&amp;#8217;s website and looking at &lt;strong&gt;his&lt;/strong&gt; list of &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/retd.html" title="List of nontechnical books recommended by Don Knuth"&gt;recommended nontechnical books&lt;/a&gt;. Topping this list, to my surprise and delight, I found:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/strong&gt; by Georges Perec (perhaps the greatest 20th century novel).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div class="amazon"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/books/life-a-users-manual.jpg" alt="Life A User's Manual"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knuth may be an expert on sorting but ranking novels by their greatness is an invidious task. Perec&amp;#8217;s masterpiece isn&amp;#8217;t that well-known, in English-speaking countries at least, hence my surprise: few who have read the book would dispute the position claimed for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book visits the rooms of a Parisian apartment block, 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier, on June 23 1978, describing the inhabitants and their stories. There&amp;#8217;s a fascination with detail and lists, with what exactly can be seen in each room, and I&amp;#8217;ll admit this detail perplexed me the first time I read the book &amp;#8212; what could be the significance of all of these &lt;strong&gt;things&lt;/strong&gt;?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On re-reading, I savour the details and the strange patterns they form. Early on, we look at the framed posters hanging on the wall of Madame de Beaumont&amp;#8217;s drawing room.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of [the posters] depicts four greedy-looking monks sitting at a table around a Camembert cheese on the label of which four greedy-looking monks &amp;#8212; the very same &amp;#8212; are again at a table around, etc. The scene is repeated distinctly four times over.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What a wonderful example of visual recursion!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span id="continue-reading"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc1" name="tocrecursive-product-packaging" id="tocrecursive-product-packaging"&gt;Recursive product packaging&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve searched shelves and the internet for a good example of recursive product packaging, like the label on the Camembert cheese in the poster, but without much luck&lt;a id="fn1link" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#fn1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I felt sure I&amp;#8217;d seen some reflexive cereal boxes. Maybe this kind of visual pun has gone out of fashion?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did find some great &lt;a href="http://www.letyrosemiophile.com/" title="Cheesy site but great labels"&gt;cheese label collections&lt;/a&gt; assembled and put online by dedicated &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=tyrosemiophile"&gt;tyrosemiophiles&lt;/a&gt;. Here&amp;#8217;s a greedy-looking monk. And here&amp;#8217;s a donkey-riding monk holding out a Camembert cheese on the label of which you can just make out a donkey-riding monk, the very same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://wordaligned.org/images/camembert-monks.jpg" alt="Camembert labels with monks"/&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc2" name="tocfractals" id="tocfractals"&gt;Fractals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal" title="Sierpinski Triangle, on Wikipedia"&gt;&lt;img style="float:right;" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/45/Sierpinski_triangle.svg/200px-Sierpinski_triangle.svg.png" alt="Sierpinski Triangle"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of mathematics, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal"&gt;fractals&lt;/a&gt; are self-similar shapes. However close you zoom in on them, they look the same. The recursive definition of the Sierpinski triangle is immediately obvious &amp;#8212; it&amp;#8217;s a triangle evenly divided into four Sierpinski triangles. What&amp;#8217;s more remarkable is that the repeating landscapes found in the most &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandelbrot_set"&gt;famous fractal of them all&lt;/a&gt; are revealed by similarly simple mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/G_GBwuYuOOs&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/G_GBwuYuOOs&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc3" name="tocfractals-in-nature" id="tocfractals-in-nature"&gt;Fractals in nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A coastline, for example, continues looks like a coastline as you zoom in on it. Here&amp;#8217;s some self-similar broccoli.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2857208130/" title="Fractal Vegetable by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3149/2857208130_14760d2a1e_m.jpg" width="240" height="180" alt="fractal-vegetable" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc4" name="tocwindows-in-windows" id="tocwindows-in-windows"&gt;Windows in windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point a webcam at a screen which monitors it, and you&amp;#8217;ll see an obvious example of visual recursion. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization software allows you to create a machine within a machine. A host operating system window can display within it a complete graphical user interface for a guest operating system.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would it be possible to take this a level deeper? Using &lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com"&gt;Parallels Desktop&lt;/a&gt; on my OS X host, running Windows XP as a guest, I installed &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com"&gt;VMware Player&lt;/a&gt; virtualization software for Windows. Next I downloaded and started up &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com/appliances/directory/308"&gt;vmTrac&lt;/a&gt;, a 113Mb VMware appliance which packages Trac, Subversion and Lighttpd on a FreeBSD core. The result appears below. I&amp;#8217;ve used Internet Explorer to access Trac, which runs as a web application on FreeBSD, itself running as a Windows XP guest, and Windows XP is a guest on OS X. And I&amp;#8217;m using Google Chrome to display this very article.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thomasguest/2865035348/" title="Windows in Windows by Thomas Guest, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3023/2865035348_ddfe1b7ed7.jpg" width="500" height="313" alt="windows-in-windows" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc5" name="tocrecursive-paintings-and-prints" id="tocrecursive-paintings-and-prints"&gt;Recursive paintings and prints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fine art world enjoys a tradition of pictures within pictures. &amp;#8220;Circle Limit II&amp;#8221;, a woodcut from the online &lt;a href="http://www.mcescher.com/"&gt;Escher picture gallery&lt;/a&gt;, depicts fishes whose scales are smaller fishes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mcescher.com/Gallery"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.mcescher.com/Gallery/recogn-bmp/LW433.jpg" alt="Circle Limit II"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vel&amp;aacute;zquez&amp;#8217;s masterpiece, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Meninas"&gt;Las Meninas&lt;/a&gt;, may not be recursive, but it&amp;#8217;s certainly self-referential. We can&amp;#8217;t see the contents of the large canvas in the picture (unless you believe the mirror reflects a portion of it) but the artist working on it is Vel&amp;aacute;zquez himself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Meninas"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/Velazquez-Meninas.jpg/526px-Velazquez-Meninas.jpg" alt="Las Meninas"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#toc6" name="tocvalenes-masterpiece" id="tocvalenes-masterpiece"&gt;Valene&amp;#8217;s masterpiece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fictional painter, Serge Valene, the longest-standing inhabitant of 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier, narrates &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;Life A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. Actually, &lt;strong&gt;depicts&lt;/strong&gt; would be a better word, for the book is conceived as a painting showing what would be seen if you removed the facade of the building and peered into each of the rooms. In the central chapter, 51, Valene imagines himself working on just such a painting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;He would be standing beside his almost finished painting, and he would be precisely in the process of painting himself, sketching in with the tip of his brush the minute silhouette of a painter in a long grey smock and a violet scarf, with his palette in his hand, painting again the infinitesimal figurine of a painter painting, once again one of these nested reflections he would have wanted to pursue to infinite depths, as if his eyes and his hand had unlimited magnifying power.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div class="amazon"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;&lt;img src="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/Images/CouvVME2.jpg" alt="Life A User's Manual"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think it spoils the book to tell you he never completes this ambitious canvas. In fact he gets no further than drawing a few charcoal lines, the sketch of a cross-section of the building which no figure, now, will ever inhabit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sketch appears as one of several appendices to the book, annotated with the names of who lived in each room, and when. It may not be finished but it does provide a key to one of the algorithms used to generate the book&amp;#8217;s structure, and, stepping outside the fiction, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;the book&lt;/a&gt; itself is finished and complete.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via &lt;a href="http://wordaligned.org/"&gt;Word Aligned&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/retd.html" title="List of nontechnical books recommended by Don Knuth"&gt;Knuth&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6rc96/list_of_nontechnical_books_recommended_by_knuth/"&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;)).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0002719991?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=wordalig-20"&gt;Life, A User&amp;#8217;s Manual&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/pages/construction.html"&gt;&lt;img src="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/jb.guinot/Images/planVME.gif" alt="Knight's tour of 11 Rue Simon-Crubellier"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
   &lt;a id="fn1" href="http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures#fn1link"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; Update: happily Stephan Schroevers &lt;a href="http://www.haloscan.com/comments/wordaligned/recursive_pictures/#34601"&gt;did rather better&lt;/a&gt;. I should have searched for &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=droste+effect"&gt;&amp;#8220;Droste effect&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=mise+en+abyme"&gt;&amp;#8220;mise en abyme&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The effect is named after a particular image, that appeared, with variations, on the tins and boxes of Droste cocoa powder, one of the main Dutch brands. It displays a nurse carrying a serving tray with a cup of hot chocolate and a box of the same brand. &amp;#8212; &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droste_effect"&gt;The Droste effect, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droste_effect"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/62/Droste.jpg" alt="Droste Cocoa powder"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
<dc:date>2008-09-17</dc:date>
<guid>http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures</guid>
<author>tag@wordaligned.org (Thomas Guest)</author>
<link>http://wordaligned.org/articles/recursive-pictures</link>
<category>Windows</category>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
